中字翻译：求人不如求己
Troy, 你别再说谎了
Troy, you ought to stop that lying.
我没有说谎
I ain't lying.
那个黑人藏着个这么大的西瓜
Nigger had a watermelon this big,
还说: 什么西瓜, Mr. Rand?
talking about, "what watermelon, Mr. Rand?"
我真想上前跟他对质, 还"什么西瓜, Mr. Rand?"
I'd like to fell out. "What watermelon, Mr. Rand?"
那个西瓜就大大的放在那
And it sitting there, big as life.
- 那Mr. Rand说了什么?   - 他没说什么
- What Mr. Rand say?   - He ain't said nothing.
他知道, 如果这个黑人那么愚蠢
He figure, if the nigger was too dumb
不知道自己在藏着一个西瓜
to know he's carrying a watermelon,
他也不能跟他说道理
he wasn't going to get much sense out of him.
他把那大西瓜藏在他的外衣下
Trying to hide that great, big, old watermelon under his coat.
害怕让那些白人看到他偷回家
Afraid to let the white man see him carry it home.
我像你一样, 我没有时间跟这种蠢人相处
I'm like you. I ain't got no time for them kinda people.
告诉我, 为何那个人看起来那么生气
Now, what he look like getting mad
在他看到从工会来的人跟Mr. Rand说话之后?
'cause he seen the man from the union talking to Mr. Rand?
他上前跟我说
He come up to me, talking about
Troy Maxson早晚会让我们失去工作的
"Troy Maxson gonna get us fired."
我跟他说:别跟我说这个
I told him, "get away from me with that."
他一边走一边说你是专门制造麻烦的人
He walked away from me calling you a troublemaker.
Mr. Rand怎样说?
What Mr. Rand say?
他没说什么, 只叫我
He ain't said nothing. Told me to go down
下星期五到理事长的办公室, 停下!
to the commissioner's office next Friday. Whoa!
他们叫我去那里会面
They called me down there to see them.
你一天还在投诉当中
Well, as long as you got your complaint filed,
他们就不能辞退你
they can't fire you.
那是一个白人跟我说的
That's what one of them white fellas tell me.
我才不担心他们会辞退我
I ain't worried about them firing me.
就因为我问了个问题, 他们就要辞退我?
What, they gonna fire me 'cause I asked a question?
我只问了个问题
That's all I did.
我问Mr. Rand
I went to Mr. Rand and I asked him.
我问他: 为何?
I asked him, "why?
为何你让所有白人负责驾驶, 而有色人种就去搬运?
Why you got all the white mens driving, and the colored lifting?"
跟他说:什么事了? 我不重要吗?
Told him, "what's the matter? Don't I count?
你以为只有白人才够聪明去驾驶吗?
Think only white fellows got sense enough to drive a truck?"
该死的, 那又不是写文件, 任何人都懂驾驶
"Hell, that ain't no paper job. Anybody can drive a truck.
你为何让所有白人驾驶, 而有色人种去搬运?
"How come you got all the whites driving and the colored lifting?"
他回答我: 去跟工会说吧
He told me, "take it to the union."
该死的, 我就去投诉
Well, hell, that's what I done.
而现在他们就想说一堆谎话隐瞒过去
Now they want to come up with this pack of lies.
我跟Brownie说了, 如果那些人向他查询
I told Brownie if the man come and ask him any questions,
就即管告诉事实
just tell the truth.
这只不过是因为你投诉了
Ain't nothing but somebody trumped it up on you
所以有人要诬蔑你
'cause you filed a complaint on.
Brownie没那么聪明
Brownie ain't got that much sense.
他什么事也不去想
Man wasn't thinking about nothing.
我只想他们改正职位描述
All I want them to do is change the job description,
给所有人一个机会去驾驶, 开车
give everybody a chance to drive the truck. Oi!
Brownie没想过这, 他不是很聪明
Brownie can't see that. He ain't got that much sense.
你怎么知道他一直在跟
How you figure he be making out
Taylor的酒吧里那个女子调情?
with that gal, be up in Taylors' all the time?
- 那个叫Alberta的女子   - 谁?
- That Alberta gal?   - Who?
Brownie.
我跟他经常在一起, 就像我们一样,
Same as you and me, getting about as much as we is.
- 心照不宣吧   - 是吗?
- Which is to say nothing.   - It is, huh?
我想你比我更猜得透他吧
Well, I figure you doing a little better than me.
我不会跟你说我在猜什么
And I ain't saying what I'm doing!
朋友, 听着, 我太了解你
Nigger, look here. I know you.
难怕你只接近了她一点
If you had gotten anywhere near that gal,
二十分钟后你就想跟谁说了
20 minutes later, you'd be looking to tell somebody.
而你第一个想要分享的对象
And the first one you gonna want to tell,
想要吹嘘的对象就是我
that you gonna want to brag to is going to be me.
我不会这样做
Oh, I ain't saying that.
我看到你在偷看她
I see where you be eyeing her.
我所有女人都看, 我不会错过任何女人
I eye all the women. I don't miss nothing.
别听别人说...
Don't never let nobody tell you
Troy Maxson不看女人
Troy Maxson don't eye the women.
你顗觎她呢
Hey, you been doing more than eyeing her.
你请她喝酒了
You done bought her a drink or two.
天啊, 我是请过她, 那又如何?
Hell, yeah, I bought her a drink. What that mean?
我也请过你喝酒
I bought you one, too.
那算什么, 就因为我请她喝了一杯?
What that mean, 'cause I buy her a drink?
我只是出于礼貌
I'm just being polite.
你请她喝一杯完全可以
It's all right to buy her one drink.
那就是出于礼貌
That's what you call being polite.
但当你继续请她喝酒
But when you want to be buying two or three,
那就是顗觎
that's what you call eyeing her.
听着, 你认识我这样久了
Look here. As long as you've known me,
你有听过我去追求女人吗?
you ever known me to chase after women?
当然有, 一直认识你以来你都有
Hell, yeah! Long as I've known you.
你忘了我认识你多久了
You're forgetting, I knew you when.
我在说在我跟Rose结婚后
I'm talking about since I been married to Rose.
噢...那倒没有
Oh... not since you been married to Rose.
我可以说, 那倒是真的
That's the truth, though. I can say that.
明白了吧, 没什么可说
All right then. Case closed.
我在Alberta的房子外看见过你
I see you be walking up around Alberta's house.
那种时候你应该在Taylor的酒吧才对
You supposed to be at Taylors',
而你却在那里出现了
and you be walking up around there.
你为何在意我去哪?
What you watching where I'm walking for?
我也没在意你去哪
I don't be watching after you.
不, 我看见你在那里不只一次
No, I seen you walking around there more than once.
当然, 我们经常在一起
Hell, you liable to see me walking anywhere.
你看到我在那里不代表什么
That don't mean nothing 'cause you seen me walking around there.
她从哪来的?
Where'd she come from, anyway?
她就好像突然出现一样
She just kinda showed up one day.
塔拉哈西, 你看到她
Tallahassee. You can look at that
就知道她是来自佛罗里达州 [塔拉哈西是其首都]
and tell she one of them Florida gals.
那里的女人都亭亭玉立
They got some big, healthy women down there.
就像树一样高大
Grow them right up out of the ground.
她有印度人的血统
She got a little bit of Indian in her.
很多在佛罗里达州的黑人都有印度人血统
Most of them niggers in Florida got some Indian in them.
我不知道她是不是混血儿
Yeah, I don't know about that Indian part,
但她真的很高大
but she damn sure big and healthy.
要是让她穿上长袜
Woman wears some big stockings.
再张开她那双诱人的腿, 真棒
Got them crazy big legs, and hips wide as the Mississippi river.
双腿并不重要
Legs don't mean nothing.
它们只会在做爱时阻碍你
You don't do nothing but push 'em out of the way.
但是臀部可重要了
But them hips,
它们坐在你上面时软呼呼的
they cushion the ride.
Troy, 不能这样算
Troy, you ain't got no sense!
那是真的, 像你年轻做爱时一样
It's the truth. Like you riding on goodyears!
你们在这里都在聊什么了?
What you all out here getting into?
女人, 你为何在意我们在聊什么?
What you worried about what we getting into for, woman?
这是男人之间的讨论
This is men talk.
我又怎么会在意呢?
What I care what you all are talking about?
Bono, 你要留下来吃晚餐吗?
Bono, you gonna stay for supper?
不了, 谢谢, Rose
No, thank you, Rose,
Lucille说她今晚要煮猪脚
but Lucille say she cooking up a pot of pigfeet.
猪脚? 那我也跟你回去了
Pigfeet? Hell, I'm going home with you.
要是你家煮猪脚, 我甚至会在你那睡一晚
I might even stay the night, you got some pigfeet.
Rose, 你里面有煮什么比猪脚还棒的吗?
You got something in there to top them pigfeet, Rose?
我在煮鸡肉, 今晚吃鸡肉和羽衣甘蓝叶
I'm cooking up some chicken. I got some chicken and collard greens.
那你先进去继续烹调
Well, you go on back in the house.
让Bono和我继续刚才的话题
Let me and Bono finish what we talking about.
这是男人之间的讨论, 我待会也有些事要跟你讨论
This is men talk. I got some talk for you later.
你也知道我要说什么的
And you know what kind of talk I mean, too.
你先进去准备下 [指做爱]
You go on in there and powder it up.
Troy, 够了!
Troy, stop it!
噢, 来吧, 女人
Oh, woman, come here.
Bono, 听着
Oh! Look here, Bono.
我第一次看到这女人时
When I first met this woman,
我就行动了
I got out that place there.
我准备好我的马匹
Hitch up my pony, saddle up my mare
因为那里有个女人在等着我
there's a woman out there for me somewhere
我到处找寻她的踪影
I looked at here, looked at there,
然后看到Rose时我就彻底被她迷住了
saw Rose, and I latched on to her.
我想也没想就上前跟她说...
I latched on to her and I told her...
我来告诉你当时到底发生了什么事
Now, I'm gonna tell you the truth.
我跟她说: 宝贝, 我不想要结婚
I latched on to her and told her, "baby, I don't want to marry.
我只想成为你的男人
"I just want to be your man."
Rose回答我... 你来告诉他, Ro
Rose told me... Tell him what you told me, Ro.
我跟他说如果他不打算长相厮守
I told him if he wasn't the marrying kind,
那就滚开, 别挡着那些想的人前来
then move out of the way, so the marrying kind could find me.
她真这么说了: 朋友, 你在挡着我
That's what she told me, "nigger, you in my way.
你在阻挡我的视线
"You blocking the view.
滚开, 让我找我的爱人
"Move out the way, so I can find me a husband."
- 我想了几天    - 你才没有
- I thought it over 2-3 days.   - Two-three days, nothing.
你那晚就回来了
You was back the same night.
我回来并跟她说: 好吧, 宝贝
I come back, told her, "okay, baby,
但我要买一只矮脚公鸡 [比正常公鸡小, 但好斗]
"but I'm gonna buy me a banty rooster
把它放在后院里
"and put him out there in the backyard.
当它看到陌生人
"And when he see a stranger come,
它就会到处跑跟大声啼叫
"he gonna flap his wings and crow."
Bono, 看这里, 我看着前门就够烦了
Look here, Bono. I done watched that front door by myself.
我担心的是[她的]后庭
It was that back door I was worried about.
Troy, 别说了, 你在撒谎
Don't talk like that! Troy, you're not but telling a lie.
但是我们结婚后才发现
Only thing was, we first got married,
忘了那公鸡吧, 因为我们根本负担不起后院
forget the rooster. We ain't had no yard.
我也明白
I hear you tell it.
Lucille和我以前住在Logan街 [美国, 丹佛]
Me and Lucille was staying down there on Logan street.
我们有两间房子, 还有个厕所在后院里
Had two rooms with the outhouse in the back.
我平常都不介意的
I ain't mind the outhouse none.
但当冬天时有阵该死的冷锋吹过
But when that goddamn wind blew through there in the winter,
我就恨死它了! [以前家里没有水管]
that's what I'm talking about!
直至今天, 我还在想
To this day, I wonder why the hell
为何我会住在那里六年之久
I ever stayed down there for six long years.
我当时也不知道可以怎办
But, see, I didn't know I could do no better.
我以为只有白人才配有室内厕所什么的
I thought only white folks had inside toilets and things.
很多人也像这样
A lot of folks don't think
安于现状
they can do no better than they're doing now.
那是些要改变的想法
Just something you gotta learn.
就像很多人还去Bella的店买东西
A lot of folks still shop at Bella's.
Bella卖的东西没问题啊, 她卖的食物也很新鲜
Ain't nothing wrong with Bella's. She got fresh food.
我不是在说她卖的食物有没有问题
I ain't said nothing about if she got fresh food.
我在说她卖的价钱
I'm talking about what she charge.
同样的货品她比A&P卖贵十美分
She charges 10 cents more than the A&P.
A&P没为我做过什么
A&P ain't never done nothing for me.
我会选择消费在我认为对的地方
I spend my money where I'm treated right.
我到Bella的店里说
I go down to Bella, say,
我要买一条面包, 星期五付钱, 她就给我了
"i need a loaf of bread, I'll pay you Friday," she gives it to me.
如果我还在
What sense that make when I got money
其他地方消费
to spend it somewhere else
把这个卖人情给我的人忘掉, 我还算什么?
and ignore the person who done right by me?
圣经里没教人忘恩负义
That ain't in the Bible.
我们不是在谈论圣经
We ain't talking about what's in the Bible.
明知道她卖贵了, 还在那买东西, 这样理智吗?
What sense it make to shop there when she overcharges?
那你去你想去的地方买
Well, you do your shopping where you want to,
我去卖过人情给我的地方买
I do my shopping where people been good to me.
噢, 我只是不认同她卖贵了而已
Oh, I don't think it's right for her to overcharge, that's all.
听着, 我该走了
Look here, I got to be getting on.
Lucille都要发怒了
Lucille gonna be raising all kind of hell.
朋友, 你要去哪, 我们还没喝完这瓶呢
Where you going, nigger? We ain't finished this pint.
先喝完吧
Come here finish this pint.
我会留下啊, 如果你请我喝的话
Well, hell, I am, if you ever turn the bottle loose.
我唯一要感谢A&P的地方
Only thing I'll say about the A&P is,
就是他们让Cory在那工作
I'm glad Cory got that job down there.
帮补一下他的开支
Help him with his school clothes and things.
Gabe搬走了, 我们有点捉襟见肘
Gabe done moved out, things getting tight around here.
他有份工作
He got that job,
至少可以照顾下自己
he can start to look out for himself.
Cory被一间大学的美式足球队录取了
Cory done got recruited by a college football team.
我跟他说过大学的美式足球队到底是怎么一回事
I told that boy about that college football stuff.
那些白人不会让他碰美式足球的
The white man ain't gonna let him get nowhere with that football.
他第一次来我就跟他解释过了
I told him when he first come to me with it.
现在你告诉我他更着迷了
Now, you come telling me he done got more tied up in it.
他该去车行工作
He ought to get recruited in how to fix cars,
还是做点能令他过活的事
or some way he can make a living.
他不是想成为职业美式足球员
He ain't talking about making no living playing football.
那只是他的兴趣而已
It's just something the boys in school do.
他们会派负责人员来
They're gonna send a recruiter by
跟你商讨, 他会跟你说
to talk to you. He'll tell you.
他不是想成为职业美式足球员
He ain't talking about making no living playing football.
被录取是个荣誉
It's an honor to be recruited.
他不会走得远的, Bono就懂
It ain't gonna get him nowhere, Bono'll tell you that.
如果他跟你一样那么有运动细胞, 他会成为伟大的球员
If he be like you in sports, he gonna be all right.
这么久以来只有两个人打棒球比你好
Ain't but two men ever played baseball good as you.
就是Babe Ruth和Josh Gibson [皆为著名棒球员]
That's Babe Ruth and Josh Gibson.
他们就是唯一比你有更多全垒打的人
Them the only two men ever hit more home runs than you.
打棒球给了我什么? 我没有地方上厕所
And what it ever get me? I ain't got a pot to piss in,
又或者靠此买过一间房子
or a window to throw it out of.
时代不同了, Troy
Times have changed since you were playing baseball, Troy.
你打棒球都是战争之前了, 很多事情都改变了
That was before the war. Times have changed a lot since then.
有什么改变了?
How the hell they done changed?
现在很多有色人种都在球队里
They got a lot of colored boys playing ball now.
棒球也好, 美式足球也好
Baseball and football.
Ro, 你说对了, 时代不同了, Troy
You right about that, Ro. Times have changed, Troy.
你只是生不逢时而已
You just come along too early.
世上没有所谓"生不逢时"
There ought not never have been no time called "too early."
以他为例...
Now you take that fellow...
那个以前在洋基队
What's that fellow they had playing
当右外野手的叫什么?
right field back then for the Yankees?
Bono, 你该记得的
You remember who I'm talking about, Bono,
在洋基队当右外野手的那个
played right field for the Yankees.
- Selkirk?    对, 就是他 [George Selkirk]
- Selkirk?   - Yeah, Selkirk, that's it!
他的职业生涯打击率是.269, 你看得出了吗?
Man's batting 269, you understand? 269!
那合理吗? 我的打击率是.432, 有37个是全垒打
What sense that make? I'm batting 432 with 37 home runs!
他的打击率才.269, 却在洋基队里当右外野手!
He's batting 269, playing right field for the Yankees!
我昨天看到Josh Gibson的女儿
I saw Josh Gibson's daughter yesterday.
她穿着破烂的鞋到处跑
She's running around with raggedy shoes on her feet.
我敢打赌Selkirk的女儿
I bet you Selkirk's daughter ain't running around
可不是穿着什么破烂的到处走
with no raggedy shoes on her feet. I bet you that.
现在很多职业棒球员都是有色人种了
They got a lot of colored baseball players now.
Jackie Robinson是第一个
Jackie Robinson was the first.
Jackie Robinson都是名星了
Folks had to wait for Jackie Robinson.
我看过无数比Jackie Robinson还会打棒球的黑人
I done seen 100 niggers play baseball better than Jackie Robinson.
我甚至看过Jackie Robinson都进不了的球队
Hell, I seen some teams Jackie Robinson couldn't even make!
还说什么Jackie Robinson?
What you talking about, Jackie Robinson?
Jackie Robinson只是个无名小卒而已!
Jackie Robinson wasn't nobody!
我要说的是如果你会打球
I'm talking about if you could play ball,
他们就该给你机会
then they ought to let you play.
而不是在意你的肤色人种
Don't matter what color you are.
还说我生不逢时
Come telling me I come along too early.
如果你会打球, 他们就该给你机会
If you can play, then they ought to let you play.
你再继续这么喝会死的
You gonna drink yourself to death.
不用喝那么多吧
You don't need to be drinking like that.
噢, 死神而已, 我都见过了
Oh! Death ain't nothing. I done seen him,
还跟他搏斗过, 不用你来跟我说
I done wrestled with him. You can't tell me nothing about death.
死神不过是个外角的快速球
Death ain't nothing but a fastball on the outside corner,
而你知道我有什么能耐
and you know what I do with that.
Bono, 看这里, 我有在说谎吗?
Look here, Bono, am I lying?
你扔个到腰水平高度的快速球
You get one of them fastballs about waist high
从外角扔过来
on the outside corner of the plate
那简直易如反掌
where you can get the meat of the bat on it,
老天啊, 我会把它打到出场外
and, good god, you could kiss it good-bye.
- 我在吹嘘吗?    - 不, 你在说事实
- Am I lying?   - No, you telling the truth.
我亲眼看见过
I seen you do it.
如果我在吹牛, 那会是天大的谎话
If I'm lying, that's 450 feet worth of lying.
死神来我来说就是这么回事
That's all death is to me.
一个从外角扔来的快速球
A fastball on the outside corner.
我不知道你为何说起死亡了?
I don't know why you want to get on talking about death?
说说又没有问题
Ain't nothing wrong with talking about death.
那是生命的一部分啊, 每个人都必经
That's a part of life! Everybody gonna die.
你会死, 我会死
You gonna die. I'm gonna die.
Bono会死, 天啊, 所有人都会死
Bono gonna die. Hell, we all gonna die.
但你也没必要继续说吧
But you ain't got to talk about it.
我不喜欢说这种事
I don't like talking about it.
那是你提起的
Well, you the one brought it up.
Bono和我刚才在说棒球
Me and Bono talking about baseball.
你突然说我会喝死
You come telling me I'm gonna drink myself to death.
不是吗, Bono?
Ain't that right, Bono?
你知道我一周只有一晚去喝酒
Now you know I drink just but one night out the week,
那是星期五晚
that's Friday night.
我不会喝多
I drink just enough to where I can handle it.
然后我就会离开, 不碰它了
Then I leaves it alone. I cuts it loose.
所以你不必担心我会喝死
So, you ain't got to worry about me drinking myself to death
因为我不害怕死亡
'cause I ain't worrying about death.
我见过他, 跟他搏斗过
I done seen him, done wrestled with him.
跟你说, Bono
Look here, Bono.
我有天看到死神举军冲向我
I look up one day, and death is marching straight at me,
像是阅兵时的士军队一样
like soldiers on parade.
当时死神大军在冲向我
The army of death was marching straight at me.
当时是1941年7月中
It was the middle of July, 1941.
然而却像冬天一般冷
And it got real cold, just like it be winter.
那时候死神他啊
And it seemed like death, himself,
好像举手碰了我肩膀一下
reached out and touched me on the shoulder.
他像我现在碰你一样, 我感受到那寒意
He touched me like I touch you now. I got cold as ice.
死神就站在那里, 对我露出不友善的笑容
Death standing there, grinning at me.
Troy, 别说了
Troy, why don't you hush that talk.
我说: 死神先生, 你想要什么? 要带走我吗?
I said, "what you want, Mr. death? You be wanting me?
你不再派你的小卒来了吗?
"You done sent your army to be getting me?"
我直直的看着他
I looked him dead in the eye.
我什么都不怕
I wasn't fearing nothing.
我准备跟他斗个你死我活, 直至现在我都是!
I was ready to tangle, just like I'm ready to tangle now!
圣经说要经常警惕
Bible says be ever vigilant.
所以我不会喝醉, 我还要耳听八方
So, I don't get but so drunk. I got to keep watch.
Troy当时进了慈善医院
Troy was right down there at mercy hospital.
你记得他那次得了肺炎
You remember he had that pneumonia,
还有发烧, 躺在床上还说些有的没的
laying there with a fever, talking plumb out his head.
当时死神站在那盯着我
And death standing there, staring at me,
手握着镰刀
carrying that sickle in his hand.
终于, 他说: 你想再活多一年吗?
Finally, he say, "you want to be bound over for another year?"
他这样说
Just like that. He say,
你想再活多一年吗?
"you want to be bound over for another year?"
我说: 去你的, 我们现在就说清楚
I said, "bound over, hell! We can settle this right now."
他听了后退后了点
He kinda fell back when I said that.
我即时龙精虎猛
And all the cold went out of me.
我伸手抢去他的镰刀
I reached down, I grabbed that sickle.
我用尽力气扔走它
I threw it as far as I could throw it,
然后我们开始埋身肉搏
and me and him commenced to wrestling.
我们打了...六...三天三夜
We wrestled for... Carry the six... Three days and three nights!
我不知道从哪儿来的力量
Now, I don't know where I got the strength from,
因为他处于优势时
'cause every time he tried to get the best of me,
我重新振作
I reached way deep down inside myself,
并又得到对抗他的力量
found the strength to do him one better.
Troy每次说起这事
Every time Troy tells that story,
都有不同的版本
he find different ways to tell it,
不同的谎话
different things to make up.
我没有胡说, 女人
I ain't making up nothing, woman.
我在说实话
I'm telling you the facts of what happened.
我跟死神搏斗了三天三夜
I wrestled with death for three days and three nights,
而现在还能站着跟你说话
and I'm standing here to tell you about it.
继续, 在最后
All right. At the end of the third night,
我们都脆弱得站不起来了
we done weakened each other to where we can't even hardly move.
死神突然站起来
Death stood up.
他披上那连帽的白色袍子
He threw on that robe, had a white robe with a hood on it.
他披上后便去寻找他的镰刀
He throwed on that robe and ent off to look for that sickle.
他说: 我会回来的, 像这样
He said, "I'll be back." Just like that. "I'll be back."
我说: 是吗? 那你得好好找我
I said, "yeah? Well, you gonna have to find me!"
我又不是傻子
I wasn't no fool.
我不会自找麻烦的
I wasn't going looking for him.
我知道死亡不是拿来开玩笑的事, 他早晚会找上我
I know death ain't nothing to play
with. And I know he's gonna get me.
我知道我早晚要加入他的大军
I know I got to join his army, his camp followers.
但我一天还有力气
But as long as I keep up my strength and see him coming,
还能保持警觉
as long as I keep up my vigilance,
他就得打上一场硬仗
he gonna have to fight to get me.
我不会轻易让他带走我
I ain't going easy.
那你看, 既然你要保持警觉
Well, look here, since you got to keep up your vigilance,
让我替你拿着那酒瓶
let me have the bottle.
该死的, 我不应该告诉你那部分
Hell, I shouldn't have told you that part.
我应该删掉那部分
I should have left out that part.
Troy一直都说这些话
Troy be talking all that stuff.
然而有一半时候他根本不知道自己在说什么
Half the time, he don't even know what he be talking about!
- Bono会了解的   - 对, 我很了解你
- Yeah, Bono know me better than that.
- That's right, I know you.
我知道你就像Uncle Remus一样 [说故事的人]
I know you got some Uncle Remus in your blood.
你有的故事比魔鬼拥有的罪人还多
You got more stories than the devil got sinners.
天啊, 我也跟他说过话
Oh, hell, I done seen him, too. Done talked to the devil.
没人想知道
Nobody wants to be hearing that stuff!
嗨, 爸
Hey, pop.
你来这里做什么?
What you come "hey, poppin'" me for?
你好吗, Rose?
How you doing, Rose?
Bono先生, 你好吗?
Mr. Bono, how you doing?
嗨, Lyons, 你呢?
Hey, Lyons, how you been?
他一定过得很好
He must've been doing all right.
他整周都没来找过我
I ain't seen him around here last week.
Troy, 放过你的儿子吧, 他特地来看你
Troy, leave your boy alone. He come by to see you
而你却又想胡说
and you want to start all that nonsense.
我没有说Lyons什么, 来喝口
I ain't bothering Lyons. Here, get you a drink.
我们知道原因
Me and him got an understanding.
我知道他为何来, 而他也知道
I know why he come by to see me, and he know I know.
爸, 别这样说, 我只是来见你一下
Come on, pop. I just stopped by to say hi,
看看你过得怎样了
see how you was doing.
- 但你昨天没来啊   - Lyons, 你留下来吃晚饭吗?
- You ain't stopped by yesterday.
- You staying for supper, Lyons?
我在煮鸡肉
I got some chicken cooking in the oven.
不了, Rose, 谢谢, 我刚巧经过这里而已
No, Rose, thanks. I just was in the neighborhood
想着进来看你们一下
and thought I'd stop by for a minute.
得了吧, 你刚巧经过这
Yeah, you was in the neighborhood all right.
老兄, 你还真会说话
Nigger, you telling the truth there.
你刚巧经过这因为我今天发薪
You was in the neighborhood 'cause it's my payday.
既然你提到了, 给我$10
Well, hell, since you mentioned it, let me have $10.
该死的, 我宁愿下地狱
I'll be damned. I'll die and go to hell
和魔鬼玩牌也不会给你
and play Blackjack with the devil before I give you $10.
我想知道你看见过的魔鬼
That's what I want to know about, that devil you done seen.
爸看见过魔鬼? 真会吹牛
Pop done seen the devil? You too much, pop.
- 对, 我见过   - 他才没有
- Yeah, I done seen him. - He ain't seen no devil.
我跟他说过那男人不是魔鬼
I told him that man ain't had nothing to do with the devil.
他把任何他不明白的事, 都称呼为魔鬼
Anything he can't understand, he want to call it the devil.
看这, Bono, 我去Hertzberger的店买些家具
Look here, Bono. I go by Hertzberger's to get some furniture.
收音机说三房寓所只售$298
You got three rooms for $298. That what it say on the radio.
三房寓所只售$298, 他还为此创作了首歌
"Three rooms, $298." He made up a little song about it.
我去到那, 他说我不能贷款
I get down there, man tell me I can't get no credit.
我每天都工作, 还不能贷款
I'm working every day, can't get no credit.
那怎办?
What to do?
我只有些破烂的家具
I got an empty house with some raggedy furniture.
Cory没有床
Cory ain't got no bed.
他在地上铺点破布就睡了
He's sleeping on a pile of rags on the floor.
每天都工作, 却不能贷款
Working every day, can't get no credit.
我回来后, Rose也看到的
I come back here, Rose'll tell you,
我非常愤怒, 想着有什么能做
madder than hell, trying to figure out what to do.
有人来敲门
Come a knock on the door.
我才住在这里三天, 有谁知道我在这?
I ain't been living but three days, who know I'm here?
我去应门, 原来是魔鬼
I open the door. Devil standing there.
一个大个子
Bigger than life.
一个白人, 穿着得体
White fella, got on good clothes and everything.
手里拿着块剪贴板
Standing there with a clipboard in his hand.
我还没说什么
Now, I ain't got to say nothing.
他就说了:
First words come out of his mouth,
我知道你需要点家具而你不能贷款
I understand you need some furniture and can't get no credit.
我都要晕倒了, 他说: 我会让你贷款
I liked to fell over.
He said, "I'll give you all the credit you want,
但你需要付利息
"but you gonna have to pay the interest on it."
我跟他说要是他给我那间寓所
Now, I told him, he give me them three rooms,
多少都行
he can charge whatever he want.
有辆货车第二天来了
Next day, a truck pull up here,
两个男人给那三间房间布置了家具
two men unload them three rooms.
驾车的那位给了我本书
Man what drove the truck give me a book.
跟我说每月初, 寄$10到书上这个地址
Said first of the month, send $10 to the address in the book,
那就可以了
everything'll be fine.
说如果你没付
Said if you miss a payment,
魔鬼会来找你, 而你需要付上更多
the devil was coming back, and there'll be hell to pay.
那是15年前的事
That was 15 years ago.
直至今天, 每月初, 我都寄$10
To this day, first day of every month, I send my $10,
非常准时, Rose可以担保
just like clockwork. Rose'll tell you.
Troy在说谎
Troy lying.
我从此没再见过那人
I ain't never seen that man since.
你说如果他不是魔鬼会是谁?
Now, you tell me, who else that gonna be but the devil?
而我没有卖掉灵魂什么的
And I ain't sold my soul or nothing like that.
我不会跟坐着货车来的魔鬼交易
No, I wouldn't have, truck with the devil over nothing like that.
但我却换来所有家具, 所以我准时寄我的十块
But I got my furniture. And I send my $10, just like clockwork.
你都付多久了?
How long you say you been paying this $10 a month?
15年
15 years.
天啊, 那你不是一早付清了吗?
Hell, ain't you finished paying for it yet?
那人要你付多少?
How much the man done charge you?
是啊, 我一早付清了
Oh, hell, I done paid for it.
早就付清了
I done paid for it 10 times over.
事实是, 我怕我不继续付要承担后果
Fact is, I'm scared to stop paying.
别听Troy说的, 家具是在Glickman先生的店买的
Troy lying. We got that furniture from Mr. Glickman.
他没有每月给谁十块
He ain't paying no $10 a month to nobody.
天啊, 女人, Bono知道我不是傻的
Hell, woman, Bono know I ain't that big a fool.
我还想说
I was just getting ready to say,
我知道有个桥下卖便宜的家具
I know where there's a bridge for sale.
我告诉你
I'll tell you this.
那人是不是魔鬼不重要
It don't matter to me if it was the devil.
他有没有给我贷款也不重要
It don't matter if the devil give credit.
- 总有人要给我吧    - 那很重要
- Somebody got to give it.   - It ought to matter.
你到处说你跟魔鬼交易了
You walking around here saying you gonna make truck with the devil,
你将来得跟上帝解释清楚
god's the one you're gonna have to answer to.
祂会作出审判
He's the one gonna be at the judgment.
听着, 爸, 给我十块
Yeah, well, look here, pop, let me have that $10.
我会还你的
I'll give it back to you.
Bonnie在医院找到工作了
Bonnie got a job working at the hospital.
Bono, 我怎跟你说的?
Bono, what did I tell you?
只有这老兄有事相求时我才会见到他
Only time I see this nigger is when he want something.
只有那种时候
That's the only time I see him.
别说这, 爸, Bono先生不想听这个
Come on, pop, Mr. Bono don't want to hear all that.
给我十块, 我说过Bonnie找到工作了吧
Let me have the $10. I told you, Bonnie's working!
她找到工作又如何了?
What that mean to me if Bonnie's working?
我不在乎, 要是她在工作, 你就去问她拿十块
I don't care if she working. Go ask her for $10 if she's working.
还说她在工作, 那你为何不工作?
Talking about Bonnie working. Why ain't you working?
爸, 你知道我不能找到正当工作
Ah, pop, you know I can't find no decent job.
我去哪找? 你知道我的过去
Where am I gonna get a job at? You know I can't get no job.
我说过, 我认识一些人
I told you, I know some people down there.
如果你想, 我可以让你来清理垃圾
I can get you on the rubbish if you want to work.
你上次有事相求时我就跟你说了
I told you that last time you come back here asking for something.
不了, 爸, 谢谢, 那不适合我
No, pop, thanks, that ain't for me.
我不想替人清理垃圾
I don't want to be carrying nobody's rubbish.
我不想做这些千篇一律的工作
I don't want to be punching nobody's time clock.
怎么了? 清理垃圾配不起你吗?
What's the matter? You too good to carry people's rubbish?
你以为那十块是哪里来的?
Where you think that $10 you talking about comes from?
我就要去清理垃圾, 然后我赚的就给你
I'm just supposed to haul people's rubbish
就因为你太懒惰?
and give my money to you 'cause you too lazy to work?
你不去工作
You're too lazy to work
然后想知道你为何没钱
and want to know why you ain't got what I got.
Bonnie在哪间医院工作? 慈善医院?
What hospital Bonnie working at, Mercy?
她在Passavant医院里的洗衣房工作 [匹兹堡医疗中心大学]
She down at Passavant, working in the laundry.
我不能给你, 我给了你十块
I ain't got nothing as it is. I give you $10,
那我接下来一星期都吃豆吗?
I got to eat beans the rest of the week?
不, 你不会拿到那十块
No, you ain't getting no $10 over here.
不至于吃豆吧
You ain't got to be eating no beans.
真不知道你为何能说出这?
I don't know why you want to say that?
我没有多余的钱!
I ain't got no extra money!
Gabe搬走了
Gabe done moved out,
钱都替Pearl小姐交房租了
giving his money over there to Miss Pearl, paying her rent.
我们都捉襟见肘了
Things done got tight around here.
我再也不能承担每次发薪金也给你
I can't afford to be giving you every payday.
我不是想你给我
I ain't asked you to give me nothing.
我是想你借给我
I asked you to loan me $10.
我知道你有十块的
I know you got $10.
我是有啊, 你知道为何吗?
Yeah, I got it. You know why I got it?
因为我到处乱花钱
'Cause I don't throw my money away on them streets.
你想过得快活, 当个音乐家
You want to live the fast life, being a musician,
有钱在俱乐部流连
running around in them clubs and things,
那就学懂照顾自己
then learn to take care of yourself.
你不会看到我请求别人帮忙
You ain't gone find me asking nobody for nothing!
这么都年来都没有
I spent too many years without.
你和我不同
Hey, you and me is two different people.
我吸取了教训, 知道该做什么
I done learned my mistake and I learned to do what's right by it.
你还想不劳而获
You still trying to get something for nothing.
没人欠你什么
Life don't owe you nothing.
是你欠自己的, 问问Bono, 他也懂
You owe it to yourself. Ask Bono. He'll tell you I'm right.
我们有各自生活的方式
You got your way of dealing with the world, I got mine.
我唯一在乎的是音乐
Only thing that matters to me is the music.
看得出来, 你吃什么不重要
Yeah, I can see that. Don't matter how you gonna eat,
哪来钱也不重要
don't matter where your next dollar coming from.
你说得真对
Yeah, you telling the truth there.
我知道我要吃饭, 但我也要生活
I know I got to eat. But I got to live, too.
我需要点什么让我每天有动力
I need something that's gonna help me get out of bed in the morning,
让我感觉到我还存在
make me feel like I belong in the world.
我不打扰谁
I don't bother nobody.
我只是玩音乐而已
I just stay with my music
因为那是我生存于世的理由
'cause that's the only way I can find to live in the world.
不给就算了, 别跟我说要做什么
Otherwise, ain't no telling what I might do.
我不是来批评你和你的生活方式
I don't come by criticizing you and how you live.
是让你借十块给我
I just come by to ask you for $10.
我不想听你说教
I don't want to hear all that about how I live.
天啊, 你母亲把你养得真好
Boy, your mama did a hell of a job raising you.
爸, 你改变不了我的, 我已经34岁了
You can't change me, pop. I'm 34 years old.
如果你想改变我
If you wanted to change me,
或许你该在我成长时陪伴左右
you should have been there when I was growing up.
我来看你, 向你借十块
I come by to see you, ask you for $10,
而你却跟我说我是如何被养育成人?
and you want to talk about how I was raised?
你根本不知道是怎么一回事
You don't know nothing about how I was raised.
给他十块吧, Troy
Let the boy have $10, Troy.
你在看什么? 你知道我没有钱的
Hell you looking at? You know I ain't got no money.
你知道我把钱放在哪
You know what I do with my money.
给他吧, 如果你想的话
Go on, give him $10 if you want him to have it.
我会, 当你交给我的时候
I will, soon as you turn it loose.
这里
There it is.
$76.22
Seventy six dollars and twenty-two cents.
看到了吗, Bono? 我只能拿回$6
You see this, Bono? I ain't gonna get but six of that back.
够了吧, 拿着, Lyons
He ought to stop telling that lie. Here, Lyons.
谢谢, Rose
Thanks, Rose.
我要走了, 下次见
Look, I got to run. I'll see you all later.
等下, 你会说"谢谢, Rose"
Wait a minute. You gonna say, "thanks, Rose,"
但你不感谢付出的那个
but you ain't gonna look to see where she got that money from.
你看到他们怎对待我吗, Bono?
You see how they do me, Bono?
我知道是你的钱, 爸
I know she got it from you, pop.
谢谢, 我会还的
Thanks. I'll give it back to you.
看, 又撒谎了
There you go, telling another lie.
你还我$10时, 你还欠着$30呢
Time I see that $10, you'll be owing me $30 more.
- 再见, Bono先生   - 保重, Lyons
- See you, Mr. Bono.    - Take care, Lyons.
爸, 谢谢, 下次见
Thanks, pop. I'll see you again.
真不知道为何他不去工作
I don't know why that boy don't go and get him a decent job
然后照顾他的女人
and take care of that woman he got.
他会找的, Troy, 那孩子还小
He'll be all right, Troy. The boy is still young!
那孩子34岁了
The boy is 34 years old.
别又开始说了
Let's not get off into all that.
我要走了, Lucille在等着我
Look here, I got to go. I got to be going. Lucille gonna be waiting.
看到这女人了吗, Bono?
See this woman, Bono?
我爱她
I love this woman.
我爱得都有点痛了
I love her so much, it hurts.
我太爱她, 我都找不到方式表达了
I love her so much, I done run out of ways of loving her,
所以我要用回最简单的
so, I got to get back to basics.
你星期一早上别来
Don't you come by my house Monday morning,
跟我说要上班了
talking about time to go to work.
- 因为我还抚摸她   - 够了, Troy
- 'Cause I'm gonna still be stroking.   - Troy, stop!
我也不在意, Rose
I ain't paying him no mind, Rose.
他只是醉了
That ain't nothing but gin talk.
即管吧, Troy! 星期一见
Go on, Troy! I'll see you Monday.
你别来, 朋友
老Don't you come by my house, nigger!
我跟你说过我到时候在做什么
I done told you what I'm gonna be doing!
星期二才来
Come back on Tuesday!
早安
Good morning.
我可以给你煮早餐, 你要吃吗?
You ready for breakfast? I can fix you some
在我挂起衣服后
soon as I finish hanging up these clothes.
我喝咖啡就行了
I got the coffee on. That's all right.
来点这个就行了
I just have some of that this morning.
昨天的彩票有结果了
That 651 hit yesterday.
Pearl小姐今个月第二次中了$1
That's the second time this month Miss Pearl hit for a dollar.
看来那些不需要的人总得到更多
Seems like those that need the least always get lucky.
贫穷的人反倒什么也没有
Poor folks can't get nothing.
数字又不认人的
Them numbers don't know nobody.
我不知道为你和Lyons都玩这个
I don't know why you fool with 'em, you and Lyons both.
用来消闲
Oh, it's something to do.
你只不过在输钱而已
You ain't doing nothing but throwing your money away.
Troy, 你知道我能控制自己
Troy, you know I don't play foolishly.
我就这里五分, 那里五分的玩
I just play a nickel here and a nickel there.
那你就花了一毛了
That's two nickels you done throwed away.
不全是, 我有时候会赢, 那就扯平了
Nah, I hit sometimes. That makes up for it.
赢了的话, 早晚会用到
Always comes in handy when I do hit.
赢的时候也不听见你抱怨
I don't hear you complaining then.
我不是在抱怨, 我只是说这很愚蠢
I ain't complaining now. I just say it's foolish,
试着在六百种组合中
trying to guess out of 600 ways
猜出正确号码
which way the number gonna come.
如果我拿到这些黑人的...
If I had all the money these niggers...
非藉美国人一周放在上面的钱
You negroes throw away on numbers in one week,
只一星期, 我就会很有钱
just one week, I'd be a rich man.
你在这里说如果和认为是件蠢事
You wishing and calling it foolish
那些人也不会停下不玩
ain't gonna stop folks from playing the numbers.
我肯定
That's one thing for sure.
再者, 玩彩票也有好处的
Besides, some good things come from playing numbers.
看看Pope玩彩票
Look where Pope done bought him
让他赚了一间餐厅
that restaurant off of numbers.
我不能接受这种人
I can't stand niggers like that.
以前他没多少钱
Man ain't had two dimes to rub together.
穿着那双破鞋漫目无的地走
He running around with his shoes all run-over,
到处问人拿香烟
bumming money for cigarettes.
好了, 中奖了
All right. Got lucky there, hit the numbers...
Troy, 我也知道
Troy, I know all about it.
我会说他很有理智
Had good sense. I'll say that for him.
没把钱花光
Man ain't throw his money away.
我看过有人四天内用掉$2000
I done see niggers go through $2,000 in four days.
他建了间餐厅
Man built him that restaurant down there.
看上去棒极了
Fix it up real nice, too.
然后他不让有些人进去
Then he won't let nobody come in it.
他们不服务黑人
Negro go in there, can't get no kind of service.
看到有个白人进去点了炖肉汤
Seen a white fella go in there, he orders a bowl of stew.
Pope从大锅里为他放了很多肉
Pope pick all the meat out of the pot for him.
那白人的炖肉汤都是肉
Man ain't had nothing but a bowl of meat!
黑人进去点同样的
Negro go in there behind him,
只会换来马铃薯和萝卜
he ain't got nothing but the potatoes and the carrots.
还说玩彩票能得到什么
Talking about what numbers do for people.
你举了个坏的例子
You picked the wrong example there.
那只让他成为一个更傻的傻子
Ain't done nothing but made a worser fool out of him
比以前傻得多了
than he already was before.
Troy.
你别再担心
You ought to stop worrying about
昨天工作时发生的事了
what happened at work yesterday.
我没在担心
I ain't worried.
他们只是叫我到理事长的办公室里
Just called me down there, the commissioner's office,
所有人都觉得我要被炒了
everybody's worried about them firing me.
我不担心
I ain't worrying about them firing me.
你也别担心了
You ain't got to worry about that.
Cory在家吗?
Where's Cory? Cory in the house?
- Cory!    - 他出去了
- Cory!   - He gone out.
出去了是吧? 他出去
Out, huh? Yeah, he going out
是因为知道我想他筑起那藩篱
'cause he know I want him to work on this fence.
我知道他害怕工作
I know how he is. That boy is scared of working.
他这辈子都没工作过
He ain't done a lick of work in his life.
他要去练习美式足球
He had to go to football practice.
教练想在赛季开始前
Coach wanted them to get in a little extra practice
多加练习
before the season start.
是啊, 我知道他在做怎样
Oh, yeah, I got his practice all right.
还没完成家务就出去
Running out of here before he gets his chores done.
Troy, 你怎么了?
Troy, what is wrong with you this morning?
什么事不合你意
Don't nothing set right with you.
回去睡足够才起来
Go on back in there, go to bed, and get up on the other side.
怎么是我有问题?
Why something got
to be wrong with me?
我没说我有什么问题
I ain't said nothing wrong with me.
你对每件事都有意见
Well, you got something to say about everything.
首先是彩票, 然后是那男人
First, it's the numbers, then it's the way the man
如何运作他的餐厅, 然后是Cory的事
run his restaurant, then you done got on Cory.
下一样会是什么?
What's it gonna be next?
抬头看看天气合不合你意
Take a look up there, see if the weather suit you.
又或者抱怨你要在这
Or is it gonna be how you gonna put up this fence
挂满衣服的院子里筑起藩篱?
with the clothes hanging in the yard?
你说对了
You hit the nail on the head then.
当然, 我这么了解你
I know you like I know the back of my hand.
进来再喝杯咖啡
Come on in here and get you some more coffee,
看看能不能让你正常点
see if that don't straighten you up.
因为你今早很不对劲
'Cause you ain't right this morning.
是Troy, 嗨
There's Troy. Hey, Troy.
嗨, Gabe
Hey, Gabe.
- 嗨, Rose   - 嗨, Gabe
- Hey, Rose.   - Hey, Gabe.
你拿着什么?
What you got there?
你想知道吗, Rose? 我有水果和蔬菜
You know what I got, Rose? I got fruits and vegetables.
你答应过给我的李子呢?
Where them plums you talking about?
我今天没有李子, 我刚才正唱着关于那个
I ain't got no plums today. I was just singing that.
我明天会带来, 我订了很多李子
I'll have some tomorrow. I put me in a big order for plums.
多到够分给圣彼得和所有人
I'll have enough plums tomorrow for Saint Peter and everybody!
Troy在生我的气
Troy mad at me.
Gabe, 我没有, 为何我要生气?
I ain't mad at you, Gabe. What I got to be mad at you about?
你又没对我做什么
You ain't done nothing to me.
我只是搬到了Pearl小姐那里
I just move over to Miss Pearl's to keep out from in your way.
我没什么打算
I ain't mean no harm by it.
谁说你有?
Who said anything about that?
我可没有说什么
I ain't said nothing about that.
你不生我的气吗?
You ain't mad at me, is you?
我没有, 如果我有, 你会知道的
I ain't made at you, Gabe.
If I was mad at you, I'd tell you about it.
进来吧
Come on, get on out of the street. Come on.
我在地下室里有两间房, 我拥有自己的门
I got me two rooms in the basement. I got my own door, too.
你想看我的钥匙吗?
You want to seemy key?
那是我的钥匙, 没有人有同一样的
That's my own key. Ain't nobody else got a key like that.
那就是我两间房间的钥匙
That's my key for my two rooms.
很好, 你有一把属于你的钥匙
That's good, Gabe. Got your own key, that's good.
你饿吗?
You hungry, Gabe?
我刚在给Troy煮早餐
I was just fixing to cook Troy some breakfast.
我吃点饼干就好了
I'll take some biscuits.
你有饼干吗?
Ooh, you got some biscuits?
你知道我在天堂时
Did you know, when I was in heaven,
我和圣彼得每早
every morning, me and Saint Peter
都会坐在门口, 吃点饼干吗?
would sit down by the gate and eat some big, fat biscuits?
那时候真棒
Oh, yeah, we had us a good time.
我们就坐着, 然后吃回饼干
We'd sit there and eat us them biscuits.
然后圣彼得会去睡一会
And then Saint Peter would go off to sleep,
叫我到审判的时候
and tell me to wake him up
叫醒他
when it's time to open the gates for the judgment.
进来吧, 我会一大堆饼干给你
Well, come on, I'll make you a big batch of biscuits.
Troy, 我看到圣彼得的名册上有你的名字
Hey, Troy. Saint Peter got your name in his book. I seen it.
写着Troy Maxson
It say, "Troy Maxson."
我跟他说: 我认识他
I say, "i know him.
我们有同样的姓 [Maxson]
He got the same name like what I got.
那是我的兄长
"That's my brother."
你要跟我说多少次这故事?
How many times you gonna tell me that, Gabe?
名册上没有我的名字, 不会有的
Ain't got my name in the book. Don't have to have my name.
我死过了, 也到过天堂
I done died and went to heaven.
但他有你的名字
But he got your name, though.
一天早上, 圣彼得在看他的名册
One morning, Saint Peter was looking at his book,
他在准备审判的到来
and he was marking it up for the judgment,
他让我看了你的名字
and he let me see your name.
在M的那一类别下
He got it in there under "M."
也有Rose的名字
He got Rose's name.
我没有亲眼看到, 但我知道的
I ain't seen it like I seen yours, but I know it's in there.
他有本很大的名册
He got a great big book! Whoo!
上面有所有存在过的人的名字
He got everybody's name what was ever been born.
他亲口告诉我的
That's what he told me.
但我亲眼看到你的名字
But I seen your name. I seen it with my own eye.
进去吧
Come in the house.
Rose会煮点什么给你吃
Rose gonna fix you something to eat now.
我不饿, 我吃了早餐了
I ain't hungry. I done had breakfast
和Jemima姨姨吃
with Aunt Jemima!
她过来, 为我煮了很多烙饼
She come by, cook me up a whole mess of flapjacks!
好了, 进去吧, Rose会...
All right. Come on, let's go in the house. Rose fix us...
还记得我们以前怎么吃烙饼吗?
Remember how we used to eat them flapjacks?
记得, 进来吧
Yes, I remember. Come on now.
- 我要走了   - Gabe!
- I got to go!   - Gabe!
- 我要走了   - Gabe, 进来吧
- I got to go!   - Gabe, come on now!
我要去卖李子
I got to go sell my plums!
我卖了点蕃茄
I done sold some tomatoes.
赚了五角, 想看吗?
Got me two quarters. Want to see?
我要储起来买个新喇叭
I'm gonna save 'em and buy me a new horn,
好让到审判时, 圣彼得能听到
so Saint Peter can hear me when it's time to open the gate.
你听到吗?
You hear that?
是地狱之犬
You hear that? That's the hellhound.
我要把它们赶走
I'm gonna chase them out of here.
走啊! 别来这!
Go on! Get out of here! Get out! Get out!
[诗歌]
Gabe在哪?
Where's Gabe?
他又到处跑了
He's gone off somewhere.
他没有好好吃饭
He ain't eating right.
Pearl小姐说他不肯吃
Miss Pearl say she can't get him to eat nothing.
你想我怎样?
What you want me to do about it, Rose?
我为他做了我能做的事
I did everything I could for the man.
我不能让他康复
I can't make him get well.
打仗时他被伤及脑袋了, 你想他怎样?
Man got half his head blown off, what you expect?
有些事还是能为他做的
Seems like something ought to be done to help him.
他也不打扰谁
The man don't bother nobody.
因为他的脑袋里有块金属碎片
He just mixed up 'cause of that metal plate
所以他才疯疯癫癫, 没理由...
he got in his head. Ain't no sense in...
谢谢, 没理由让他住在医院
Thank you. Ain't no sense in sending him to the hospital.
至少他会吃点什么
At least he'd be eating right.
他们会照顾他
They could help him take care of himself.
没有人想被锁起来
Don't nobody want to be locked up, Rose.
你为何想锁起他?
What you want to lock the man up for?
他上战场
Man going down there,
跟日本人打仗
over there and fight that war, messing with them japs,
炸伤了脑袋
getting half his head blown off.
他们随便赔了三千块, 我都接受了
They give him a lousy $3,000. I got to swoop down on that.
你又要说这个了吗?
Is you fixing to get into that again?
他的脑袋里有块金属碎片
He got a metal plate in his head.
而那就是我得到这间房子的原因
That's the only reason I got a roof over my head
就因为那金属碎片
is 'cause of that metal plate.
你没理由自责的
Ain't no sense in you blaming yourself for nothing.
他不能管理好那笔钱
Gabe was in no condition to manage that money.
你为他做了正确的事
You done what was right by him.
没人能说你不是
Can't nobody say you ain't done what was right by him.
看看你照顾他多久了
Look how long you took care of him.
一直至到他想要有自己的地方, 才搬去Pearl小姐那
Till he wanted his own place
and moved over there with Miss Pearl.
女人, 那不是我想说的, 我只是...
That ain't what I'm saying, woman. I'm just...
我只是在说事实
I'm just stating the facts.
要是我的弟弟没有受伤
If my brother didn't have a metal plate in his head,
我就不会有上厕所的地方
I wouldn't have a pot to piss in
不会有个后院
or a window to throw it out of.
我都53岁了...
And I'm 53...
你要去哪?
Where you going off to?
你近期每个星期六都出去
You been running out of here every Saturday for weeks.
我以为你会筑起那藩篱
I thought you were gonna work on this fence.
我去Taylor的酒吧里
I'm gonna go down to Taylors' and, uh...
妈妈?
Mama?
Cory, 你爸爸对你今早还没完成家务
Oh, Cory. Your daddy like to have a fit with you
就跑出去非常愤怒
running out of here this morning without doing your chores.
你还好吗?
You all right?
他说你本该帮忙筑起藩篱
He say you supposed to be helping him with the fence.
我说过要去练习啊
I told you I had to go to practice.
他过去几个星期六都这样说
And he's been saying that the last four or five Saturdays,
然后就跑到Taylor的酒吧
and then don't ever do nothing but go down to Taylors'.
你有跟他说录取的事吗?
You told him about the recruiter?
有
Yeah, I told him.
- 那他怎么说? - 他没说什么
- Well, what'd he say? - He didn't say nothing too much.
在他回来前快完成家务
Go on and get started on your chores before he gets back here.
在他回来又要抱怨前
Go on and scrub down them steps
快去刷刷地板
before he come back here hollering and carrying on!
现在啊, 小子
Go! Boy, go!
继续吧, Troy, 你早晚会把我吓死的
Go on, Troy. You liked to scare me to death.
比赛怎么了?
What was the score of the game?
Lucille在电话说过, 但我没留意
Lucille had me on the phone. I couldn't keep up with it.
我为何在意比赛了? 来吧, 女人
What do I care about the game? Come here, woman.
我以为你去Taylor那里
I thought you went down to Taylors'
就是为了看比赛, 让我走
to listen to the game. Go on, Troy.
我以为你要筑起那藩篱
I thought you're supposed to be putting up the fence.
我会去的, 在我处理好...
I'll put it up when I finish with what...
我手上的事
Is at hand.
快去吧, 真不懂你的
Go on, Troy. I ain't studying you!
但我懂你, 我会好好的弄清楚你
I'm studying you. I'm finna do my homework.
够了
Troy, you better leave me alone!
Cory回来了吗?
Where Cory? That boy brought his butt home yet?
他在上面做家务
He's upstairs doing his chores.
Cory, 快下来...
Cory, get your butt...
- 你去哪?   - 很快会来
- Where you going?   - I'll be right back.
- 何时?   - 就街口那
- When?   - I'm just going right down the street.
去哪? 跟谁?
Where? Who?
Troy, 进去吧
Troy, go in the house.
你到现在才回来吗?
You just now coming here from leaving this morning?
- 对, 我要去练习   - 对什么?
- Yeah, I had to go to football practice... - Yeah, what?
对, 先生
Yes, sir.
我才不看你一会
I ain't but two seconds off you, no way.
那垃圾箱都要满了
That garbage sitting in there, overflowing.
你没做过家务
You ain't done none of your chores.
现在也没礼貌
Now you come in here, talking about, "yeah."
我刚想做, 爸
I was just getting ready to do my chores now, pop.
你的首要是星期六帮我筑起藩篱
Your first chore is to help me with this fence on Saturday.
所有事都放在那之后
Everything else come after that.
去拿木锯, 我们要锯开这些木板
Now, get that saw, we gonna cut these boards.
嘿, 爸
Hey, pop.
你为何不买电视?
Why don't you buy a TV?
我要来做什么?
What I want with a TV? What I want one of them for?
现在每人家里都有一台
Everybody got one. Earl, Ba Bra, Jesse.
我不是在问谁有电视, 我是问要来做什么?
I ain't asked who had one, I said what I want with one?
所以你可以看啊, 现在有很多不同的节目
So, you can watch it. They got lots of things on TV.
- 棒球也有   - 是吗?
- Baseball and everything.   - Yeah?
我们可以看世界大赛
We could watch the world series.
- 那买电视要多少钱?    - 我不清楚
- Yeah, how much this TV cost?   - I don't know.
我看见过优惠价二百块
They got 'em on sale for about $200.
- 二百块?   - 那不算贵, 爸
- $200?   - That ain't that much, pop.
是啊, 才二百块而已
No, that's just $200.
你有留意那屋顶吗?
You see that roof you got sitting over your head at night?
我来告诉你那屋顶的事
Let me tell you something about that roof.
那屋顶已经十年没涂上焦油了
It's been 10 years since that roof was last tarred.
然后到了冬天下雪时
See, now snow come this winter,
雪积聚在屋顶上
sit up on that roof like it is,
然后一点点的慢慢地渗透到里面
it's gonna seep inside, just gonna be a little bit,
你甚至不会注意到
you ain't gonna hardly notice it,
然后当你发现时
then next thing you know,
早已渗透到各处
it's gonna be leaking all over the house.
然后因为积水, 木材会腐蚀
Then the wood rot from all that water,
到时候你就需要把整个屋顶换掉
and you gonna need a whole new roof.
你猜要多少才能修好?
Now how much you think it cost to get that roof fixed?
- 我不知道   - $264现金, 明白了吗?
- I don't know.   - $264 cash money. See?
当你在想买电视
While you be thinking about a TV,
我就得担心头上的屋顶
I got to be thinking about the roof
又或是要修理的东西
or whatever else go wrong around here.
如果你有二百块, 你会怎做?
Now if you had $200, what would you do?
修理屋顶还是买电视?
Fix the roof, or buy a TV?
买电视, 当屋顶开始渗水时
I'd buy a TV. And when the roof started to leak,
我才修理它
if it needed fixing, I'd fix it.
你哪来的钱?
Where you gonna get your money from?
你都花在买电视上了
You done spent it on a TV.
到时候你在里面
You gonna sit up in there,
看着漏水滴到你的新电视上吗?
let that water run all over your brand-new TV?
爸, 我知道你有钱的
Pop, you got the money. I know you do.
- 在哪?    - 银行里
- Where I got it at, huh?   - In the bank.
你想看我的存摺吗?
You want to see my bank book?
你想看我那$73.22的存款吗?
You want to see that $73.22 I got sitting up in there?
你不需要一次付清
You don't have to pay for it all at one time.
可以先给首期, 之后分期付款
You can put a down payment on it, and carry it on with you.
除非情况紧急, 我才不会让自己欠别人东西
Not me. I ain't owing nobody nothing if I can help it.
迟了付款, 他们就会来带走它
Miss a payment, they come and snatch it right out of your house.
那你就白付了, 明白了吗?
Then what you got, huh? See?
如果我有整整$200块, 我会选择买电视
Now, when I get $200 clear, I'll buy me a TV.
要是我手上有$264块, 我就会选择修理屋顶
Right now, when I get $264, I'm gonna get that roof fixed.
爸...
Oh, pop...
如果你想买电视
You go get you $200
就自己赚$200块
and buy you a TV if you want to.
我的钱要花在更实用的地方
I got better things to do with my money.
我赚不到$200, 我甚至没见过$200
I can't get $200. I ain't never seen $200.
好吧, 我跟你说
All right, I'll tell you what.
我们各人付$100
You get $100, I'll put the other $100 with it.
好吧, 等着我
All right, I'm gonna show you.
现在给我看你如何切开这些木板
Yeah, show me how you can cut these boards right now.
拿着, 那值$200块
There you go. That's $200 worth.
- 匹兹堡海盗队今天赢了   - 是吗?
- The Pirates won today.   - Yeah?
连续赢五场了
That makes five in a row.
我没在意海盗队, 他们都只有白人球员
I ain't thinking about no Pirates. They got an all-white team.
他们有个波多黎各的球员, Clemente是吧?
Got that boy, though, that Puerto Rican boy, Clemente?
也不让他出出场
Don't even half play him.
如果给那孩子机会, 他会是位伟大的球员
That boy could be something if they'd give him a chance.
让他上一天场, 隔天又坐板凳了
Play him one day, sit him on the bench the next.
他也常上场啊
He gets lots of chances to play.
我在说每天都上场, 当正选
I'm talking about playing every day, playing regular,
这才能学到更多啊
so you can get your timing, that's what I'm talking about.
他们队里也有些白人不是每天都能上场
They got some white guys on the team that don't play every day.
你总不能让全部人上场
You can't play everybody at the same time.
如果有个白人球员是当后备的
If they got a white fellow sitting on the bench,
你可以肯定他根本不会打棒球
you can bet your last dollar he can't play.
有色人种要出色两倍才能当正选
Colored guy got to be twice as good to get on the team.
那就是我不想你进球队的原因
That's why I don't want you getting all tied up in them sports.
进去了又如何?
Man on the team, what it get him?
球队的有色人种不被重用
Got colored on the team, don't even use him.
如同没有他们一样, 所有球队都是这样的
Same as not having them. All them teams the same.
亚特兰大勇士队也有Hank Aaron和Wes Covington
The Braves got Hank Aaron and Wes Covington.
Hank Aaron已经有43个全垒打了, 算上今天两个的话
Hank Aaron hit two home runs today. That makes 43.
Aaron不算什么, 那是你该做的
Aaron ain't nobody. That's what you supposed to do.
你该全力以赴
That's how the game's supposed to be played.
没别的, 不过是
Ain't nothing to it. It's a matter of getting
抓准时机然后挥棒
your timing and follow through.
我现在也可以打43个全垒打
Hell, I can hit 43 home runs right now.
你不能在美国职业棒球大联盟里打得出来
Not off no Major-League pitcher, you couldn't.
我们在黑人联盟里有更强的投手
We had better pitching in the negro leagues.
我在Satchel Paige身上打过七次全垒打
I hit seven home runs off of Satchel Paige.
你不会找到比他更好的球员
You can't get no better than that.
Sandy Koufax, 他是联盟里三振次数最多的
Sandy Koufax, he leading the league in strikeouts.
我不是在想Sandy Koufax的事
I ain't thinking about no Sandy Koufax.
还有Warren Spahn和Lew Burdette, 我猜你...
You got Warren Spahn and Lew Burdette. I bet you...
我不想再说了
I'm through with it now.
去锯木板吧
Go and cut them boards.
你妈妈跟我说你被大学美式足球队录取了
Your mama told me you got recruited by a college football team.
真有此事吗?
Is that right?
对, Zellman教练说
Yeah, coach Zellman say
晚点会有负责人跟你商讨
the recruiter gonna be coming by to talk to you.
让你签同意书
Get you to sign the permission papers.
我以为你会在A&P里工作
I thought you was supposed to be working down the A&P.
你放学后不是应该到那里工作吗?
Ain't you supposed to be working down there after school?
Stawicki先生说他会替我留着位子
Mr. Stawicki say he gonna hold my job for me
直到赛季结束
until after the football season.
他说下周起, 我可以只上周末的班
He said starting next week, I can work weekends.
小子, 我以为我们说好了
Boy, I thought we had an understanding about this football stuff.
你应该继续完成家务
You supposed to keep up with your chores,
继续在A&P工作
hold your job down there at the A&P.
你今天大半天不在
You ain't been around here all day on a Saturday,
也没完成家务
ain't none of your chores done.
现在你说你辞职了?
Now you come telling me you done quit your job?
- 我周末也会上班啊   - 当然了
- I'm gonna be working weekends. - You damn right you are!
那负责人也不必到来
And ain't no need for nobody to be coming around here,
跟我说签署的事
talking to me about signing nothing.
爸, 你不能这样做
Pop, you can't do that.
他大老远从北卡罗莱纳州来
He's coming all the way from north Carolina.
我才不在乎
I don't care where he coming from!
听着, 小子
Look, boy,
那些白人无论如何也不会让你
the white man ain't gonna let you
碰美式足球的
get nowhere with no football no way.
你继续你的学业, 所以你可以...
Now you get your book-learning, so you can, uh,
在A&P有进升的机会, 还有学习维修车子
work your way up at the A&P
and learn how to fix cars,
或者建筑, 让自己有一技傍身
or build houses, get you a trade.
那样你才有竞争力
This way, you got something can't nobody take away from you.
你的双手
You go in and learn how to put your hands to good use
该做比清理垃圾更好的工作
besides hauling other people's garbage.
我的成绩很好, 爸
I get good grades, pop.
那就是他们会跟你商讨的原因
That's why the recruiter want to talk with you.
你的成绩也要好才能被录取的
You got to keep up your grades to get recruited.
这样我就有机会上大学
This way, I'll be going to college, I'll get a chance.
首先, 你去A&P那拿回你的工作
First, you get your butt down there and get your job back.
Stawicki先生已经聘请了其他人
Mr. Stawicki done already hired somebody else
因为我跟他说我要打美式足球
'cause I told him I was playing football.
我比我想像中还蠢
You a bigger fool than I thought.
你竟然让别人代替了你的位置
You gonna let somebody take away your job,
好让你能打什么美式足球
so you can play some football.
你上哪赚钱
Where you gonna get your money
照顾你的女友什么的?
to take care of your girlfriend and whatnot?
到底有多蠢
What kind of foolishness is that
才会让别人代替了自己?
to let somebody take away your job?
我周末还是会去工作的
I'm still gonna be working weekends.
不, 你去找另一份工作
No. You getting out of here and finding you another job.
别这样, 爸, 我还得练习呢
Come on, pop. I gotta practice.
我不能同时工作和练习
I can't work after school and play football, too.
Zellman教练说球队需要我
The team needs me, that's what Coach Zellman say.
我才不介意他说什么, 我说了算, 明白了吗?
I don't care what nobody say. I'm the boss. You understand?
我是你的父亲, 我说的才算
I'm the boss around here. I do the only saying what counts.
- 别这样...    - 我问你: 你明白了吗?
- Come on...  - I asked you, "do you understand?"
- 明白   - 什么?
- Yeah.   - What?
- 明白, 先生    - 好了
- Yes, sir.   - All right.
你去A&P看看能不能取回你的工作
You get on down there to that A&P and see if you can get your job back.
如果只能二选其一, 那就放弃进球队吧
If you can't do both, then you quit the football team.
人生不如意事十常八九
You got to take the crookeds with the straights.
明白, 先生
Yes, sir.
我可以问你点事吗?
Can I ask you a question?
你又要问什么?
What the hell you got to ask me?
你该问Stawicki先生工作的事
Mr. Stawicki the one you got the questions for.
你为何从不喜欢我?
How come you ain't never liked me?
喜欢你? 谁说我一定要喜欢你?
Like you? Who the hell said I got to like you?
有什么规定要我一定要喜欢你?
What law is there say I got to like you?
既然站在我面前
You want to stand up in front of my face
问这蠢极了的问题
and ask a damn fool-ass question like that.
还扯什么喜欢谁
Talk about liking somebody.
说话时站近点, 小子
Come here, boy, when I talk to you.
该死的, 站好, 我问你
Straighten up, god damn it! I asked you a question.
- 有什么规定要我一定要喜欢你?   - 没有
- What law is there say I got to like you?   - None.
正是, 你三餐温饱吗?
All right, then. Don't you eat every day?
我问你问题时, 你就得回答我
Answer me when I talk to you.
- 你三餐温饱吗?   - 对
- Don't you eat every day?   - Yeah.
小子, 你一天在我的地方
Nigger, as long as you in my house,
你就得加在句子最后加上"先生"
you put a "Sir" on the end of it when you talk to me.
- 是, 先生   - 你每天都有饭吃?
- Yes, sir.   - You eat every day?
- 是, 先生    - 有地方住?
- Yes, sir.   - Got a roof over your head?
- 是, 先生   - 有衣服穿?
- Yes, sir.   - Got clothes on your back?
- 是, 先生   - 原因呢?
- Yes, sir.   - Why you think that is?
- 全因为你   - 我当然知道是因为我
- 'Cause of you.   - Hell, I know it's 'cause of me.
但你认为是因为什么?
But why do you think that is?
因为你喜欢我?
'Cause you like me?
"喜欢"你
"Like" you.
我每天一大清早出去工作
I go out of here every morning,
还得时时刻刻忍受那些白人 [crackers带侮辱之意]
I bust my butt putting up with them crackers every day
才算得上"喜欢"你
'cause I "like" you.
你简直是我见过最愚蠢的人, 那是我的职责
You about the biggest fool I ever saw. It's my job.
我的责任
It's my responsibility.
一个男人就该照顾他的家庭
A man is supposed to take care of his family.
你住在我的房子里, 吃我买回来的食物
You live in my house, fill your belly with my food,
我照顾你是因为你是我的儿子啊
put your behind on my bed because you're my son.
而不是我喜欢你, 照顾你是我的职责
Not 'cause I like you. 'Cause it's my duty to take care of you.
我得承担起这个责任
I owe a responsibility to you.
现在我就说清楚
Now, let's get this straight right here and now,
以免你将来又说同样的话
before it go along any further.
我不需要喜欢你
I ain't got to like you.
Rand先生每星期发薪给我不是因为他喜欢我
Mr. Rand don't give me my money come payday 'cause he like me.
是因为他欠我的
He give it to me 'cause he owe me.
现在我已给了所有我该给你的
Now I done give you everything I got to give you.
我把你带到这个世界上啊!
I give you your life!
你妈妈和我都商讨好各自的职责
Me and your mama worked that out between us,
而喜欢你不是我的工作之一
and liking your black ass wasn't part of the bargain.
你从今起别再
Now don't you go through life
担心别人是否喜欢你
worrying about whether somebody like you, or not.
你该想他们没有负了你
You best be making sure they're doing right by you.
- 明白了吗?   - 明白, 先生
- You understand what I'm saying?   - Yes, sir.
那现在滚开, 去A&P拿回你的工作
Then get the hell out of my face and get on down to that A&P!
你为何就不让那孩子打美式足球呢, Troy?
Why don't you go ahead and let the boy play football, Troy?
他只想像你一样在运动有点成就
He just want to be like you with the sports.
我不想他重蹈覆辙
I don't want him to be like me.
我想他走条和我完全不同的路
I want him to get as far away from my life
越不同越好
as he possibly can get.
你是我生命中唯一遇过的好事, Rose
You the only decent thing ever happened to me, Rose.
我希望他找个像你一样好的女人
And I wish him that.
除此之外我不希望他像我一样
But I don't wish him nothing else from my life.
我在他出生的那天就决定
I decided 17 years ago,
那孩子不要参与什么运动
that boy wasn't gonna get involved in no sports.
在我明白运动里的不公之后
Not after what they did to me in the sports.
你为何就不承认你当时不能进职业联盟是因为年纪?
Why don't you just admit you were too old for the Major Leagues?
就承认一次?
For once, why don't you just admit that?
别跟我来年纪这套
Don't you come tellin' me I was too old.
是因为我是有色人种而已, 我现在都53岁了
I just wasn't the right color. Hell, I'm 53 years old,
但我肯定我能打出比S的.269更好的成绩
I can do better than Selkirk's .269 right now.
过了40岁还怎样打棒球?
How were you gonna play ball when you were over 40?
有时候你说的话真不合逻辑
Sometimes, I can't get no sense out of you.
我很清醒, 女人
I got good sense, woman.
我清楚知道别让运动伤了他的身心
I got sense enough not to let that boy get hurt playing no sports.
你太疼爱他了
You mothering the boy too much.
让他老是担心别人是否喜欢自己
Worrying about whether people "like" him or not.
那孩子做的所有事, 都是为了给你看
Everything that boy do, he do for you.
他想你称赞他, 仅此而已
He wants you to say, "good job, son." That's all.
Rose, 我没时间做这些事, 他好好的活着
I ain't got time for that, Rose. He's alive, he's healthy.
就得自己找出路, 我也得继续自己的生活
He's got to make his own way. I made mine.
他将来出社会后
Ain't nobody gonna hold his hand
没有人会时常照顾他的
when he get out there in the world.
Troy, 时代不同了
Times have changed, Troy.
人会变的
People change.
世界在变, 而你根本不知道
The world changing, and you can't even see it.
女人, 我尽我所能地工作
Woman, I do the best I can do.
每星期五我带着
I come in here every Friday,
一袋马铃薯和一桶猪油回来
I carry a sack of potatoes and a bucket of lard.
你们才得以不用工作
You all line up at the door with your hands out.
我连最后的钱都用在你们身上
I give you the lint from my pockets.
我付出了我的血汗
I give you my sweat and my blood.
我无法给你们同情, 早已用光了
I ain't got no tears. I done spent them.
我们晚上到楼上做爱
We go upstairs in that room at night, I fall down on you
在你里面给了我唯一所剩的
and try to blast a hole into forever.
星期一早上起来, 带着桌上煮好的午餐
I get up Monday morning, find my lunch on the table,
出去继续我的生活
go out and make my way.
试着捱到星期五
Find my strength to get me through to next Friday.
那就是我能给的, Rose
That's all I got, Rose.
那已经是我能给你们的全部了
That's all I got to give.
已经没什么可以再给你们了!
Can't give nothing else!
Maxson先生?
Mr. Maxson?
理事长想见你
Commissioner will see you now.
Rose!
嘿, Ro!
Hey, Ro!
我真想看到Rand先生当时的糗样
I wish I could've seen Mr. Rand's face when he told you.
他听了判决后都说不出话来了
He couldn't get it out his mouth. Liked to bit his tongue.
当他们叫我到理事长的办公室时
When they called me down there to the commissioner's office,
Rand像所有人一样都以为他们要炒了我
he thought they was gonna fire me, like everybody else.
我可没有这样想
Oh, I didn't think they was gonna fire you.
我以为他们要给你警告信
I thought they's gonna put you on the warning paper.
嘿, Rose! 对, Rand先生这下一定无话可说了
Hey, Rose! Yeah, Mr. Rand liked to bit his tongue.
我看到你跑到Taylor的酒吧
I see you run right down there to Taylors'
告诉那个叫Alberta的女子
and told that Alberta gal.
嘿, Rose! 我跟所有人都会说的, 嘿, Ro!
Hey, Rose! I told everybody. Hey, Ro!
我去那兑现支票 [花钱]
I went down there to cash my check.
嘿!
Hey!
别叫了, 我知道你回来了
Hush all that hollering. I know you out here.
理事长怎说了?
What they say down at the commissioner's office?
我叫你的时候你就该立刻回应我, 女人
You supposed to come when I call you, woman.
Bono也懂
Bono will tell you that.
你叫Lucille时她不也立刻回应吗?
Don't Lucille come when you call her?
闭嘴吧老兄, 我又不是狗
Man, hush your mouth. I ain't no dog.
说什么立刻回应你
Talk about come when you call me.
Bono, 看到了吗? 我以前有只狗
You hear this, Bono? I used to have me an old dog
也像这样自以为高人一等
get uppity like that.
你喊他来, 他也不理会
You say, "come here, Blue,"he just lay there, look at you.
最后通常都是被追着打, 为了教训他
End up getting a stick chasin' him away, trying to make him come.
我不在意你和你的狗
I ain't studying you and your dog.
我记得你总会唱起歌来
I remember you used to sing that old song.
没有人想听啊
Nobody wants to hear that old song.
他唱起来时, 总让Cory到处跑
Used to have Cory runnin' around here singin' that song.
我也记得那首歌
Hell, I remember that song myself.
那是我爸爸的歌
That's my daddy's song.
他创作的
My daddy made up that song.
我才不在乎谁作的, 没有人想听你唱的
I don't care who made it up. Don't nobody want to hear you sing it.
你这么兴奋回来, 我就猜到他们没有炒了你
You come in here carrying on, I reckon they ain't fired you.
理事长到底说了什么?
What they say down there at
the commissioner's office?
Rose, 听着, Rand先生在理事长会见我后
Look here, Rose. Mr. Rand called me in his office
叫我到他的办公室
after I got back from talkin' to them people down there.
他叫我进去并说
He called me in his office and told me...
他们要让我当司机!
They was making me a driver!
- Troy, 你在说笑吧!   - 不信问Bono
- Troy, you kidding!   - No, I ain't. Ask Bono.
那真好, Troy
That's great, Troy.
那你再不用跟那些人纠缠了
Now you don't have to hassle them people no more.
天啊, 没想到今天你会来
Oh, hell. I didn't think I was gonna see you today.
我以为你在监狱里
I thought you was in jail.
听到消息说他们扫荡Seefus的店
Got it all over the courier about them raiding Seefus' place
那个你跟那些不伦不类的家伙经常去的地方
where you be hanging out with all them thugs.
嘿, 爸, 那跟我没关系
Hey, pop, that ain't got nothing to do with me.
我没在那赌博
I don't go down there gambling.
我只是去那跟乐队交流
I just go down there to sit in with the band.
那赌博跟我沾不上关系
I ain't got nothing to do with the gambling part.
他们那里有些很好的音乐人
They got some good music down there.
那里只有流氓而已
They got some rogues is what they got.
Bono先生你还好吗? 你好, Rose
How you been, Mr. Bono? Hi, Rose.
我知道你今晚在Crawford Grill有演出 [爵士乐俱乐部]
I see where you playing down at the Crawford Grill tonight.
你怎么又不带Bonnie来?
How come you ain't brought Bonnie like I told you?
你该带上她来
You shoulda brought Bonnie.
她很久没来过了
She ain't been by in a month of Sundays.
我刚巧路过而已
I was just in the neighborhood.
- 想着见你们一面   - 又来了
- Thought I'd stop by.   - Here it comes.
你爸爸升职了
Your daddy got a promotion on the rubbish.
他是第一个驾驶垃圾车的有色人种
He gonna be the first colored driver.
什么也不用做
Ain't got to do nothin' but sit up there
像白人一样坐着看报纸就行了
and read the paper, like them white fellas.
爸, 如果你识字的话, 那会是件好事
Hey, pop, if you knew how to read, you'd be all right.
不不, 你指如果这老兄懂得驾驶的话
Nah, nah. You mean if the nigger knew how to drive,
那才是件好事
he'd be all right.
一直跟那些人争论驾车的问题
Been fighting with them people about driving
然而连驾照也没有
and ain't even got a license.
Rand先生知道你没有驾照的吧?
Mr. Rand know you ain't got no driver's license?
驾车很容易
Driving ain't nothing.
就是扭軚盘而已
All you do is point the truck where you want it to go.
并不难
Driving ain't nothing.
他们知道你没有驾照吗?
Do they know you ain't got no driver's license?
那才是我问的
That's what I'm talkin' about.
我不是问你驾驶是否容易
I ain't asked if driving was easy.
我问你Rand先生是否知道你没有驾照一事
I asked if Mr. Rand know you ain't got no driver's license.
那人没必要知道我的事
The man ain't got to know my business.
待他发现时我已经有两三个驾照了
Time he find out, I have two or three of them driver's license.
- 听着, 爸   - 我就知道你会这么说
- Say, look here, pop.   - I knew it was coming.
我知道你要说什么
I knew what kinda "look here, pop" that was.
那小子又要问我拿钱了
Nigger finna ask me for some money.
今天是星期五, 又是我的发薪日
It's Friday night, it's my payday.
那些没被拘捕的流氓会在Avenue大道流连
All them rogues down on the Avenue, the ones that ain't in jail,
Lyons赶着去跟他们会合
and Lyons is hopping in his shoes to get down there with them.
听着, 爸
Now, see, pop,
如果你让别人说完他要说的
if you gave somebody else a chance to talk sometime,
你就会知道我要还你答应过的十块
you'd see I was fixing to pay you back your $10 like I told you.
拿着, 我说过待Bonnie发薪了我会还你的
Here. I told you I'd pay you when Bonnie got paid.
不, 你自己留着那十块, 存到银行里
No, you keep that $10. Put it in the bank.
下次你觉得又要来这里向我拿钱时
Next time you feel like you wanna come by here
你就从银行拿出这十块
and ask me for somethin', you go down there and get that.
拿着属于你的十块吧, 爸
Here you go your $10, pop.
我说过我不想你给我
I told you, I don't want you to give me nothing.
我只想借而已
I just wanted to borrow $10.
不, 你留着下次用
No, you keep that for the next time you want to ask me.
别这样, 爸, 拿着吧
Come on, pop, here go your $10.
Troy, 你为何不让那孩子还钱?
Troy, why don't you let the boy pay you back?
你替他拿吧, Rose, 如果你不拿
Here you go, Rose. If you don't take it,
接下来六个月他又要不断唠叨此事了
I'm gonna hear about it for the next six months.
你也可以顺道给出你的那份薪金, Troy
You can hand yours over, too, Troy.
Bono, 你看到他们怎对待我了吗
You see this, Bono? You see how they do me?
看到, Lucille也是这样做
Yeah, Lucille do me the same way.
嘿, 是Troy的儿子啊
Hey. Hey, there's Troy's boy!
Gabe叔叔, 你最近好吗?
How you doing, Uncle Gabe?
Lyons!
万兽之王
The king of the jungle!
嘿, Rose, 我有朵玫瑰花给你
Rose. Hey, Rose, I got a flower for you.
我亲自摘的, 就跟你名字一样的玫瑰
I picked it myself. That's the same rose like you is.
你真有心, Gabe
Aw, that's right nice of you, Gabe.
Gabe叔叔, 你最近在做什么?
What you been doing, Uncle Gabe?
噢, 我一直在追赶地狱之犬
Oh, I been chasing hellhounds and waiting for the time
并等着告诉圣彼得打开天堂的门
to tell Saint Peter to open the gates.
你在追赶地狱之犬?
You been chasing hellhounds, huh?
你做得很正确
Well, you doing the right thing, Uncle Gabe.
- 总有人要去赶走他们   - 是的, 我也知道
- Somebody's got to chase 'em.   - Oh, yeah, I know it.
魔鬼很强大, 不是那么容易打败
The devil's strong. The devil ain't no pushover.
地狱之犬一直在寻找人类的气息 [应为sniff, 非snip]
Hellhounds snipping at everybody's heels.
但我已经准备好喇叭, 等待审判日的来临
But I got my trumpet waiting on the judgment time.
为了哈米吉多顿之战作准备吗? [圣经中世界末日最后一战]
Waiting on the Battle of Armageddon, huh?
噢, 那眨眼就会结束
Oh, ain't gonna be too much of a battle
当上帝挥动审判之剑时
when god get to waving that judgment sword.
如果天堂的门关上的话, 那时候人们就得费时
But the people's gonna have a hell of a time
等待进入天堂了
trying to get into heaven if them gates ain't open.
你听到这吗, 爸?
You hear this, pop?
Gabe叔叔, 你人真好
Uncle Gabe, you all right.
Lyons.
万兽之王
The king of the jungle!
Gabe, 你留下来吃晚餐吗?
You stayin' for supper, Gabe?
你要我煮你的份吗?
You want me to fix you a plate?
我要份三明治就好了, 不用煮我的份
I'll just take a sandwich, Rose. I don't want no plate.
我喜欢用双手拿着来吃, 三明治好了
I want to eat with my hands. I'll take a sandwich.
你呢Lyons? 留下吗? 在煮牛小排呢
What about you, Lyons? You stayin'? Got some short ribs cooking.
不了, 我通常在演出完结后才用餐的
Nah. I won't eat nothing till after we finish playing.
你应该来看看我演出, 爸
You ought to come down, listen to me play, pop.
噢, 我不喜欢那些像中国音乐一样的嘈音
Oh, I don't like all that Chinese music, all that noise.
去洗手吧, Gabe, 我现在弄三明治
Go in there and wash up, Gabe. I'll fix you a sandwich.
Troy在生我的气
Troy mad at me.
你为何生他的气?
What you mad at Uncle Gabe for?
他以为Troy为了
He think Troy mad at him
他搬到Pearl那里而生气
'cause he moved over there to Miss Pearl's.
我才没有生气, 他可以住他想住的地方
I ain't mad at the man. He can live where he want to live at.
他为何搬到那里? Pearl小姐任何人都不喜欢
Well, what he move over there for? Miss Pearl don't like nobody.
噢, 她不介意他在, 还对他颇好
Oh, she don't mind him none. She treat him real nice.
她就不允许他唱歌而已
She just don't allow all that singing.
她不介意他在为她付租金, 仅此而已
She don't mind that rent he be paying. That's what she don't mind.
Troy, 我不想再跟你讨论此事
Troy, I ain't goin' through that with you no more.
他搬到那因为他想要有自己的地方
He moved over there 'cause he wanted his own place.
他可以随他所想的做
He can come and go as he please.
他可以在这里做他想做的, 我也不介意
He can come and go as he please here. I wasn't stoppin' him.
我也没规定他什么
I wasn't putting no rules on the man.
你明知道那是两码子的事
That ain't the same thing, and you know it.
我不想再讨论这话题
Now that's the last I wanna hear about that.
我不想再听到Gabe和Miss Pearl之间的事
I don't wanna hear nothin' else about Gabe and Miss Pearl.
还有下周...
And next week...
我准备好了, Rose
I'm ready for my sandwich, Rose.
还有下周, 当从学校来的负责人到来
And next week, when that recruiter come from that school,
我要你签署让Cory进美式足球队
I want you to sign that paper and go on and let Cory play football.
我不想再听你说起此事
That'll be the last I have to hear about that.
Cory被录取了? 他要到哪所学校?
Cory got recruited? What school he goin' to?
我不想再理会Cory的事
I ain't thinking about Cory nothing.
那小子把这里当成他的地方
Boy walking around here smelling his piss,
以为可以为所欲为
thinking he gonna do what he want to do,
不听我的说话
irregardless of what I say.
Bono, 听着, 我离开理事长的办公室后
Look here, Bono, I left the commissioner's office
去了A&P那里
and went down to the A&P.
那小子根本没在那工作, 他跟我说谎了
That boy ain't workin' down there, he lied to me.
说他取回了工作, 周末得上班什么的
Tellin' me he got his job back, tellin' me he workin' weekend,
说他课后在上班
tellin' me he workin' after school.
Stawicki说他根本没来上班
Mr. Stawicki says he ain't working down there at all.
Cory只是长大了而已
Cory just growing up.
他有了自己的想法, 不能再听你说的
He just bustin' at the seams, tryin' to fill out your shoes.
我才不在意他想什么
I don't care what he doing.
当他到了反叛期
When he get to the place where he want to disobey me,
那就是出外打拼的时候了, Bono也懂
then it's time for him to move on. Bono will tell you that.
我肯定他不能违抗他父亲后
I bet he ain't never disobeyed his daddy
不用受罚
without paying the consequences.
我根本没机会违抗他
I ain't never had the chance.
我父亲到处走, 我根本没看过他
My daddy came on through, but I ain't never knew him to see him.
或者他在想什么, 去哪了
Or what he had on his mind, or where he went.
就四海为家, 寻找新大陆
Just moving on through. Searching out the new land.
那就是以前的人用的
That's what the old folks used to call it.
一个人要是到处搬, 不停换女人
See a fella moving around from place to place, woman to woman,
他们叫这"寻找新大陆"
they call it "searching out the new land."
我也不清楚他有没有找到
I can't say if he ever found it.
我来到这地方, 也不想有孩子
I come along, didn't want no kids.
我也不知道我能否安定下来
I didn't know if I was gonna be in one place long enough
当个爸爸
to fix on 'em right as their daddy.
我想不如还是寻找新大陆算了
I figured I was going searching, too.
没想过我跟Lucille在一起的时间
As it turn out, I been hooked up with Lucille
也几乎有你爸爸和Rose在一起那么久了
for near about as long as your daddy been with Rose.
已经16年了
Going on 16 years.
有时候我真希望自己不认识我的父亲
Sometimes, I wish I'd never known my daddy.
他不在意孩子过得怎样, 对他来说毫不重要
He ain't cared nothing about no kids. A kid to him wasn't nothing.
他只想你快点成人
All he wanted you to do was learn how to walk,
好让你能去工作赚钱给他
so he could start you to working.
吃饭时, 他总先吃, 你只吃他剩下的
Come to eating, he ate first. Anything left over, that's what you got.
他会吃掉所有东西, 而你只分到那么一点
Man would sit down, eat two chickens, and give you the wing.
爸, 别胡说了, 天下父母都会让子女吃饱
You ought to stop that, pop. Everybody feed their kids.
不管时势有多艰难, 天下父母都疼爱子女
No matter how hard times is, everybody care about their kids.
确保他们三餐温饱
Make sure they have something to eat.
我父亲唯一在意的
Only thing my daddy cared about
就是叫我们搬那一卷卷的棉花给Lubin先生
was getting them bales of cotton in to Mr. Lubin.
那是他唯一在意的事
That's the only thing that mattered to him.
以前我都在想他为何还活着
Sometimes, I used to wonder why he was still living,
为何魔鬼还没带走他
why the devil hadn't come and got him.
快把棉花搬到Lubin先生那
"Get them bales of cotton in to Mr. Lubin."
后来才知道我父亲欠Lubin钱
Find out he owe him money.
当他知道此地不宜久留时
He should have just went on and left
他就该跑路
when he saw he couldn't get nowhere.
至少我会那样做
That's what I would've done.
他怎留下11个孩子就走? 还有走去哪?
How he gonna leave with 11 kids? And where he gonna go?
他只懂耕作, 他根本无路可逃
He ain't knew nothing but how to farm. No, he was trapped.
我想他也知道, 但我也会为他说一句...
I think he knew it, too. But I'll say this for him...
他觉得他有责任照顾我们
He felt a responsibility toward us.
虽然不像我预期一样体贴
May not have treated us like I felt he should have,
但他要是没有良心
but without that responsibility,
大可以留下我们, 自己跑路
he could have run off and left us,
再另起炉灶
made his own way.
很多人也这样
A lot of them did.
你说你父亲的那一代吗?
Back in those days, what you talkin' about?
他们每天离开房子
They walk out their front door
无论多日晒雨淋, 都在街上一直走
and take off down one road or
another and just keep on walkin'.
对, 这才像话
There you go. That's what I'm talkin' about.
一直走到他们遇到下一间房子
Just keep on walking till they come to something else.
你没听过大迁徙吗? [一战时黑人从美国南部迁北]
Ain't you never heard of nobody having the walking blues?
那就是你叫那些跑路的人
Now, that's what you call it when you just take off like that.
我父亲不是你说的那种
My daddy ain't had no walking blues. What you talking about?
他留下来了
He stayed right there with his family,
但他坏事做尽
but he was just as evil as he could be!
我妈妈接受不了他和他的性格
My mama couldn't stand him. Couldn't stand that evilness.
我8岁时她就离开了
She run off when I was about eight.
她有一晚静悄悄的走, 跟我说她会回来
She sneaked off one night, told me she was coming back for me.
自那我就再没有见过她
I ain't never seen her no more.
他有过的女人终究都会离开他, 他不是个好人
All his women run off and left him. He wasn't good for nobody.
轮到我离家的时候
My turn come to head out.
我当时14岁
I was 14,
跟Joe Canewell的女儿打得火热
got to sniffing around Joe Canewell's daughter.
我们家有只老骡子叫Greyboy
We had this old mule called "Greyboy".
我父亲叫我出去耕作
My daddy sent me out to do some plowing.
让我有机会跟Joe Canewell的女儿谈谈情
I got to fooling around with Joe Canewell's daughter.
我们找到了一个隐蔽的地方抚摸大家
Found us a nice spot, got real cozy with each other.
她当时13岁, 所以我们都知道大家发育了
She was about 13, so we done figured we grown anyway.
我们在溪河附近, 互相抚摸
So, we were down there by the creek, enjoying ourselves,
把正事都放一边
ain't thinking about nothing.
怎料绑着Greyboy的绳子松开了
Didn't know Greyboy had gotten loose,
它跑回家里, 我父亲就知道事有蹊跷
wandered back to the house, and my daddy was lookin' for me.
他找到我们时, 看到我们还在抚摸大家
So, we down there enjoying ourselves when he come up on us.
我们不知所措
Surprised us.
他拿着骡子身上的皮带
Had them leather straps off that mule,
开始不停地打我
commenced to whupping me like there was no tomorrow.
我站起来, 当时心感侮辱又愤怒
I jump up. I'm mad, embarrassed.
又很害怕他
I was scared of my daddy.
他开始打我时
Now, when he commenced to whipping on me,
很自然地我就逃跑吧
quite naturally, I run to get out of the way.
我想他是因为我没有完成工作而生气
Now, I think he's mad 'cause I ain't done my work.
但我看到他故意让我落跑
But I see where he's chasing me off,
然后想去独占这个女孩
so he can have the gal for himself.
当我想透了
When I see what the matter of it was,
我变得不再害怕他, 自那, 我成为了一个男人
I lost all fear of my daddy, and right there, I became a man.
才14岁
Fourteen years of age.
是时候轮到我作主了
Now, it's my turn to run him off.
我拿起他刚才用的皮带
I picked up them same reins he used on me.
然后开始打起他来
I picked up them reins, I commenced to whupping on him.
那女孩落荒而逃
Gal jump up, she run off.
当他转过来看着我时
When he turned to face me,
我终于知道为何魔鬼没有带走他
I knew why the devil never come and get him
因为他就是魔鬼
'cause he was the devil himself.
我忘了之后发生什么了
I don't know what happened.
我醒过来, 躺在溪河旁
I woke up, laying there by the creek,
我们养的老狗Blue, 他在舔我的脸
and Blue, this old dog we had, he was licking my face.
我的双眼肿极了
Both my eyes were swoll shut.
我以为我瞎了, 什么都看不到
I thought I was blind, I couldn't see nothing.
就躺在那里哭
I just laid there and cried.
我也不知道该怎办
And I didn't know what I was gonna do.
但我知道是时候离家出走了
But I knew the time had come for me to leave my daddy's house.
突然间我感觉到世界之大
Suddenly, the world got big, and...
费了我很多时间才弄清楚
It was a long time before I could cut it down to where I could handle it.
弄清楚的期间, 我发现
Part of that cutting down was where I got to the place
其实他在我心底下, 在怒吼着想出来
where I could feel him kicking in my blood,
而我和他之所以不同
and I knew the only thing that separated us
只是我们不是生于同一个时代而已
was a matter of a few years.
Gabe叔叔, 你在吃什么?
What you got there, Uncle Gabe?
我在吃火腿三明治
I got me a ham sandwich.
Rose给我弄了火腿三明治
Rose gave me a ham sandwich.
除了Gabriel外, 我没再联系家里的人
I lost touch with everybody except Gabriel.
但...
But...
我希望他已经死了
I hope he's dead.
我希望他能找到点安慰
I hope he found some peace.
真是个沉重的故事, 爸
That's a heavy story, pop.
我都不知道你14岁就离家了
I didn't know you left home when you was 14.
14岁太早独立了
Fourteen's kinda young to be on your own.
要是我的话真不知道该怎办
I don't know what I would've done.
我在那溪河站了起来, 向莫比尔出发
Well, I got up from that creek, walked on down to Mobile.
我不想再耕作了, 我想我在城市会找到更好的工作
I was through with farming.
I figured I'd do better in the cities.
所以我徒步走了200英里到莫比尔
So, I walked the 200 miles to Mobile.
等下, 你才没有徒步走200英里, 爸
Wait a minute, you ain't walked no 200 miles, pop.
没有人想这样做
Ain't nobody gonna walk no 200 miles.
那是段很长的距离啊!
You talking about some walking there!
以前唯一到其他地方的方法就是徒步
That's the only way you got anywhere back in them days.
妈的, 我会选择搭便车
Shit! Damn if I wouldn't have hitched a ride with somebody.
哪来的便车?
Who you gonna hitch it with?
那时候才没有现在的车和科技
There ain't no cars and things like they got now.
当时是1918年
We talking about 1918.
你们在这里聊什么?
What you all out here gettin' into?
我跟Lyons说他现时的生活比以前好多了
I'm telling Lyons how good he got it.
他根本不知道我在说什么
He don't know nothing about this I'm talking.
Lyons, 刚才Bonnie打来了
Lyons, that was Bonnie on the phone.
她说你约好了去接她下班
She says you supposed to pick her up.
知道了, Rose
Yeah, okay, Rose.
我到了莫比尔
I walked on down to Mobile,
搭了驶向这边来的人便车
hitched up with some fellows that was coming up this way.
到了才发现
Got up here and found out,
不但找不到工作
not only could you not get a job,
也找不到住处
you couldn't find no place to live.
我以为自己自由了
I thought I was in freedom.
有色人种都住在里弗班克 [加州城市]
Colored folks living down there on the Riverbanks
随便哪里都好
in whatever kind of shelter they could find for themselves.
有些在桥下睡
Right down there under the Brady Street Bridge.
有些在自己用木条和沥青纸搭建的帐篷睡
Living down there in shacks made out of sticks and tar paper.
那时候我都要崩溃了
Messed around down there.
无恶不作, 开始偷窃
Went from bad to worse. Started stealing.
开始时是食物, 然后我想到偷钱
First, it was food. Then I figure I steal me some money,
可以买食物, 鞋等
I can buy me some food, buy me some shoes, too.
一样接一样, 最后遇见你的妈妈
One thing led to another. Met your mama.
当时还小, 急着想成为个男人
I was young, anxious to be a man.
我遇到你妈妈后有了你, 怎办了?
I met your mama and had you. Why'd I do that for?
我得多养两人
Now, I got to worry about feeding you and her.
得要偷更多才行
Got to steal three times as much.
我有一天在外面, 想着对谁下手
I went out one day looking for somebody to rob.
对, 我当时是个小偷
That's what I was, I was a robber.
我不会隐瞒
I'mma tell you the truth.
直至今天我还是心感惭愧, 但那是事实
I'm ashamed of it today, but it's the truth.
我找到目标, 掏出了我的小刀
I went to rob this fella, I pull out my knife.
他拿出了枪, 想也不想就射在我胸口上
He pulled out a gun, shot me in the chest.
那感觉
It felt like somebody had taken
就像有人拿着灼热的铁块烙印在我身上
a hot branding iron and laid it on me.
他射了我之后, 我跳上前以小刀还击
Now, when he shot me, I jumped at him with my knife,
他们说我杀了他
and they say I killed him.
让我坐了15年监牢
Locked me up, put me in the penitentiary for 15 years.
我在里面认识了Bono
That's where I met Bono.
学会了打棒球
Where I learned how to play baseball.
出来后才发现你妈妈带走了你
Got out that place, and your mama had taken you,
在一个没有我的环境下继续生活
went on to make a life without me.
15年是段很长的时间
Fifteen years was a long time for her to wait.
但那15年让我改正了
But that 15 years cured me of that robbing stuff.
Rose会告诉你
Rose'll tell you.
我再遇到她时, 她问我
I first met her, she ask me if I had
是否已经将那无知改掉了
gotten all that foolishness out of my system.
我说: 宝目, 只剩你和棒球
I said, "baby, it's you and baseball,
对我来说是重要的, 听到吗, Bono?
"all what count to me." You hear me, Bono?
而我也真的那样想, 她说: 哪样较重要?
And I meant it, too. She said, "which one come first?"
我说: 当然是棒球
I said, "well, ain't no doubt it's baseball.
但要是你留下来和我白头到老
"But you stick and get old with me,
我们的爱会比对棒球的爱更长寿
"and we'll both outlive this baseball."
我说对了吗, Rose?
Am I right, Rose?
那是真的
And it's true.
老兄, 闭嘴吧, 你才没有说过
Man, hush your mouth. You ain't say no such thing.
你当时说"宝贝你知道你永远都是最重要的"
Talkin' about, "baby, you know you'll always be number one with me."
那才是你所说的
That's what you was talking.
那就是为何我那么爱这个女人
That's why I love this woman.
Rose总会提醒你
Rose will keep you straight.
如果你误入歧途, 她总会提醒你
You get off the track, she'll straighten you up.
Lyons, 你快点去接Bonnie
Lyons, you better get on up and get Bonnie.
她在等你呢
She waiting on you.
- 嘿, 爸   - 什么?
- Hey, pop.   - Yeah?
你应该来看看我表演
You ought to come down to the grill, hear me play.
老兄, 我才不去
Oh, man, I ain't goin' down there.
我太老了, 不适合到俱乐部
I'm too old to be hanging out in them clubs.
你得很出色才能在[酒吧和]烤肉店演出
You got to be good to play down at the grill.
来吧, 爸
Come on, pop.
我明天还得早起
I got to get up in the morning.
你不用待到很晚
Well, you ain't gotta stay long.
不了, 我打算吃了晚餐就去睡
No, I'm gonna eat my supper and go to bed.
那我走了, 下次见
Well, I got to go. I'll see you later.
你别在我的发薪日出现
Don't you come by my house on my payday!
还有下次来先打电话, 让别人知道
And pick up the phone, let somebody know you coming,
也带上Bonnie, 你知道我很想见她
and bring Bonnie, you know I'm always glad to see her.
好的, Rose, 保重
I'll do that, Rose. You take care now.
- 下次见, 爸   - 好吧
- See you, pop.    - All right.
再见, Bono先生
See you, Mr. Bono.
再见, Gabe叔叔
See you, Uncle Gabe!
Lyons! 万兽之王!
Lyons! King of the jungle!
晚餐好了吗, 女人?
Supper ready, woman?
我们有点事要做
Me and you got some business to take care of.
- 我会让你爽翻天   - Troy, 我说过了
- I'mma tear it up, too.   - Troy, I done told you now!
天啊, 女人, 是Bono而已, 他就像家人一样
Oh, hell, woman, it's Bono. Bono like family.
我已经认识这朋友...
I done know this nigger since...
- 我认识你多久了?   - 很久了
- How long have I known you?  - It's been a long time.
我自Skippy还是小朋友的时候就认识这朋友 [应为电影]
I done known this nigger since Skippy was a pup!
经历了不少日子
Me and him done been through some times!
你说对了
You sure are right about that.
我认识他甚至比认识你还长, Rose
Hell, I known him longer than I known you, Rose,
至今我们还是好朋友
and we still standin' shoulder to shoulder.
夫复何求啊Bono
Look here, Bono, a man can't ask for no more than that.
我爱你, 朋友
I love you, nigger.
天啊别来这套, 我也爱你
Oh, hell! I love you, too.
但我得回去, 你在这里能见你的女人
But I got to get home, see my woman. You got yours in hand.
我得回去才能见到她
I got to go get mine.
你为何这样做, 爸?
What you do that for, pop?
Cory, 什么事了?
What's the matter? Cory, what's the matter?
爸到学校跟Zellman教练说
Pop done went up to the school and told Coach Zellman
我不能继续打美式足球
I can't play football no more.
也不让我比赛和练习
Wouldn't even let me play the game.
他告诉教练叫球队负责人别来找他
Told him to tell the recruiter not to come.
- Troy.   - 你叫我做什么?
- Troy.   - What you Troying me for?
对, 我的确做了, 那小子知道原因
Yeah, I did it. And the boy knows why I did it.
你为何要这样对我? 那是我唯一的机会啊!
Why you wanna do that to me? That was the one chance I had!
让Cory打美式足球又没什么问题, Troy
Ain't nothing wrong with Cory playing football, Troy.
那小子欺骗了我
The boy lied to me.
我跟那臭小子说过: 你想继续打
I told the nigger, "you want to play football,
就得继续完成家务
"you keep up with your chores
继续在A&P工作, 那就是条件
"hold that job down at the A&P." That was the conditions.
我去过Stawicki先生那里...
I stopped down to see Mr. Stawicki...
赛季期间我下课后不能去工作, 爸
I can't work after school during the football season, pop.
我跟你说过Stawicki先生会为我留着位置
I tried to tell you Mr. Stawicki was holding my job for me.
你从不听别人说话
You don't never want to listen to nobody,
然后就替我自作主张?
and then you wanna go and do this to me?
我没对你做什么, 这全都是你自找的
I ain't done nothin' to you. You done it to yourself.
就因为你以前没有机会!
Just 'cause you didn't get a chance!
你只是害怕我会比你有成就, 仅此而已!
You're just scared I'm gonna be better than you, that's all!
- 来这   - Troy
- Come here.   - Troy.
Troy.
Troy
捡起它
Pick it up.
戴上它
Put it on.
系隐
Strap it up.
好了, 听着
All right. See
你犯了个错误
You done made a mistake.
- 我什么都没做   - 我来告诉你
- I didn't even do nothing - I'll tell you what your mistake was.
你挥棒了, 但你没打中球
You swung at the ball and you didn't hit it.
那是第一振, 你现在在打击区
That's strike one. You in the batter's box now.
你挥棒但没打中, 明白了吗?
You swung and you missed, see?
那是第一振
That's strike one.
你最别被三振
Don't you strike out.
Cory, 你何不进来
Cory, why don't you come on in here,
帮我清洁一下杯柜?
help me clean out these cupboards?
我不会退出球队的, 我不在意爸爸说什么
I ain't quitting the team. I don't care what papa says.
他回来后我会跟他商讨的
I'll talk to him when he get back.
他得去看你叔叔Gabe
He had to go see about your Uncle Gabe.
警察又拘捕了他
Police done arrested him again.
说他扰乱秩序
Said he was disturbing the peace.
他很快回来
He'll be back directly.
进来帮我刷刷杯柜
Come on in here and help me clean out these cupboards.
来吧
Come on.
Troy, 他们怎说了
Troy, what they say down there?
没说什么, 我给了他们$50, 他们就让他走了
They ain't said nothing. I give them $50, they let him go.
晚点再跟你说
I'll talk to you about it.
Cory在哪?
Where Cory?
他在里面帮我清洁杯柜
He in the house, helping me clean out these cupboards.
那去叫他出来这里
All right, tell him to get his butt out here.
他们只想要钱
All they want is the money.
我去接他回来已经六七次了
This makes six, seven times, I done went down there and got him.
他们大老远看到我来, 就已经伸出手向我拿钱
See me coming, they stick out their hands.
我明白, 他们只在意钱
Yeah, I know what you mean.
That's all they care about, that money.
不在意对错
They don't care about what's right.
傻子, 你为何拿了硬木材回来?
Nigger, why you got to go and get some hardwood?
你只不过是筑个藩篱而已
You ain't doing nothin' but building a little old fence.
去找些松木, 那才是你需要的
Get you some soft pinewood. That's all you need.
我知道自己在做什么, 这才是用在室外的木材
I know what I'm doing. This outside wood.
松木是用在室内的
You put pinewood inside the house.
松木是室内用的, 这些是室外的
Pinewood inside wood. This here the outside wood.
告诉我, 籓篱要建在哪?
Now tell me, where the fence gonna be?
你不需用上这种木材
You don't need this wood.
你可以用松木建
You can put it up with pinewood,
那籓篱会比你更长寿
and it'll stand as long as you gonna be here looking at it.
你怎知道我何时死, 朋友?
How you know how long I'm gonna be here, nigger?
天啊, 我可能长生不老呢
Hell, I might live forever.
我会比那老头Horsely活得久
I'll live longer than old man Horsely.
Magee以前也总是这样说
That's what Magee used to say.
Magee是个大傻子, 你告诉我谁会
Ah, Magee a damn fool. Now you tell me who you ever heard of
用生锈的钳子替自己拔牙?
gonna pull their own teeth with a pair of rusty pliers?
他们是老一辈的人
They're old folks.
我祖父以前也用钳子拔牙
My granddaddy used to pull his teeth with pliers.
以前没有牙医会为有色人种服务
They ain't had no dentists for colored folk back then.
至少用清洁的钳子吧, 懂吗?
Well, get clean pliers. You understand? Clean pliers.
先消毒, 再者, 今非昔比了
Sterilize them. Besides, we ain't living back then.
他只需要到Goldblum牙医就行了
All he had to do was go down to Doc Goldblum's.
我看到你和那来自塔拉哈西的女孩, Alberta
I see where you and that Tallahassee gal, that Alberta,
看到你们老在一起
see where you all done got tight.
什么意思?
What you mean, "got tight"?
我看到你经常和她打闹
I see where you be laughing and joking with her all the time.
我跟每个人也是这样做, 你懂我的, Bono
I laugh and joke with 'em all. Bono, you know me.
不是平常那种打闹
Ain't the kind of laughing and joking I'm talking about.
Bono先生, 你好吗?
How you doing, Mr. Bono?
Cory, 拿起Bono手中的木锯开始工作
Cory, get that saw from Bono and cut some wood.
他说木材太硬很难锯断
He talking about wood too hard to cut.
退后点, Jim
Go on. Stand back there, Jim.
让那小子展示给你看
Let the young boy show you how it's done.
无任欢迎
He's sure welcome to it.
看他壮得像Joe Louis一样 [职业拳击手]
Look at that. Big, ol' strong boy, looks like Joe Louis.
天啊, 我真的老了
Hell, I must be getting old
看到他工作才感到岁月不饶人
the way I'm watching that boy whip through that wood.
我真不懂为何妈妈想要在后院筑起籓篱
I don't see why mama wants a fence around no yard no way.
我也想知道
Damn if I know, either.
我不知道她在提防什么
I don't know what the hell she keeping out with it.
她又没什么别人想要的东西
She ain't got nothing nobody wants.
有些人建籓篱来提防外面的人
Some people build fences to keep people out,
有些人则用来让围栏内的人留住
and other people build fences to keep people in.
Rose想要留住你们, 她太爱你们了
Rose wants to hold on to you all. She loves you.
朋友, 我不需要别人来提醒我我的妻子爱我
Hell, nigger, I don't need nobody to tell me my wife loves me.
Cory, 进去找找看有没有另一把木锯
Cory, go in the house and see if you can find the other saw.
在哪?
Where's it at?
我说找找看, 看到你找到为止
I said find it. Look for it till you find it.
把围栏内的人留住是什么意思?
What is that supposed to mean? Want to keep us in?
Troy
Troy,
我几乎大半辈子都认识你
I done known you seem like damn near my whole life.
你和Rose两个都是, 认识很久了
You and Rose both. I known both of you all for a long time.
我还记得当初你遇见Rose的时候
I remember when you met Rose.
以前你在公园打棒球时
When you was hitting them baseball out of the park.
很多女孩都追求你
A lot of them old gals was after you then.
你简直是万人迷
You had the pick of the litter.
当你选了Rose, 我很替你高兴
When you picked Rose, I was happy for you.
那是第一次我觉得你有点理智
That's the first time I knew you had any sense.
我想: 我的好朋友Troy知道他想要的
I said, "my man Troy knows what he's doing.
我会跟着他, 他可能会带我到前所未到过的地方
"I'm gonna follow this nigger, he might take me somewhere."
而我真的跟着你了
I been following you, too.
我学到了一大堆关于因果的事
I done learned a whole heap of
things about life watching you.
学到了哪些是屎
I done learned how to tell where the shit lies.
哪些是苜蓿 [分辨是非]
How to tell it from the alfalfa.
你教了我很多事
You done learned me a lot of things.
教我不要重蹈覆辙
Showed me how to not make the same mistakes.
不要一步登天
To take life as it come along,
一步一步的来
keep putting one foot in front of the other.
Rose是个好女人, Troy
Rose is a good woman, Troy.
我知道
I know she a good woman.
我跟她结婚18年了
I've been married to her for 18 years.
你到底想说什么, Bono?
What you got on your mind, Bono?
我只是说她是个好女人, 没别的
I just say she's a good woman, like I say anything.
我不必暗示什么
I ain't got to have nothing on my mind.
你就抛出一句她是个好女人
You just say she a good woman and leave it
然后没有下文?
hanging out there like that?
你为何突然说她是个好女人?
Why are you telling me she a good woman?
她爱你, Troy
She loves you, Troy. Rose loves you.
你说我不配吗?
You saying I don't measure up?
我认为那就是你想说的
That's what you tryin' to say.
我不配她因为我在和别的女人在外面
I don't measure up 'cause I'm seeing this other gal.
我知道你暗示什么
I know what you tryin' to say.
我知道Rose对你来说有多大意义
I know what Rose means to you, Troy.
我只是想说我不想看见你对她不忠
I'm just tryin' to say I don't want to see you mess up.
我明白
Yeah.
感谢你
Well, I appreciate that, Bono.
如果你对Lucille不忠
If you was messing around on Lucille,
我也会跟你说同一番话
I'd be telling you the same thing.
那就是我要说的了
That's all I got to say.
我会说是因为我爱你们两个
I just say that 'cause I love you both.
对
Oh. Yeah.
你懂我的为人, 我没在外面拈花惹草
You know me. I wasn't out there looking for nothing.
我肯定你不会找到比Rose更好的女人
You can't find a better woman than Rose, I know that.
但看来Alberta总黏着我
But it seems like this woman just stuck on to me
我怎说她都不肯离开
where I can't shake her loose.
我试过跟她吵架或者避开她
I done wrestled with it and tried to throw her off,
但她反倒更缠着我了
but now she stuck on tighter.
而现在她打算这辈子跟定我了
And now she stuck on for good.
你总是告诉我你有分寸
You's in control. That's what you tell me all the time.
你会对你做过的事负责任
You responsible for what you do.
我没在逃避责任
I ain't ducking the responsibility of it.
只要问心无愧就可以了
As long as it set right in my heart, then I'm okay.
因为那是我的宗旨, 它会告诉我是非对错
'Cause that's all I listen to. It tell me right and wrong every time.
而我也没说要对Rose不忠
And I ain't talking about doing Rose no bad turn.
我爱她
I love Rose.
她跟我这么久了
She done carried me a long ways,
我为此而爱她, 尊重她
and I love and respect her for that.
我知道
I know you do.
那就是为什么我不想看到你伤害她
That's why I don't want to see you hurt her.
但要是她发现了怎办?
But what you gonna do when she finds out?
你到时候会剩下什么?
What you got then?
你脚踏两只船
You try to juggle both of them,
早晚也得二舍其一
sooner or later, you gonna drop one of them.
- 那是常识   - 我明白, Bono
- That's common sense. - I know what you're saying, Bono.
我一直在想办法
I been trying to figure a way to work it out.
尽快, Troy
Work it out right, Troy.
我不是想对你们的家事指指点点
I ain't trying to get all up between you and Rose's business,
但趁事情还没转坏前赶快解决
but work it, so it come out right.
那我来介入你们的家事
Hell, I get all between you and Lucille's business.
你打算何时买
And when you gonna buy that woman
她一直想要的冰箱?
that refrigerator she be wanting?
别告诉我你没钱
And don't tell me you ain't got no money.
我知道谁替你打理财务
I know who your banker is.
钱该花在Lucille的冰箱上而不是放在梅隆银行内
Mellon don't need that money as bad as Lucille wants that refrigerator.
我很清楚
I know that.
- 告诉你吧   - 什么?
- Tell you what I'll do.   - What?
当你为Rose建成籓篱时
When you finish building this fence for Rose,
我就给Lucille买冰箱
I'll buy Lucille that refrigerator.
你会后悔的
You done stuck your foot in your mouth now.
朋友, 你要去哪?
Hey, nigger, where you going?
我得回家
I'm going home.
你不是在想我会帮你吧
I know you don't expect me to help you now.
我得保住我的钱
I'm protecting my money.
我想看你一个人慢慢的建
I want to see you put that fence up by yourself.
那就是我想看的
That's what I want to see.
没有我的帮忙, 六个月后你仍然毫无头绪
You'll be here another six months without me.
朋友, 那样不对啊
Nigger, you ain't right.
当谈到我的钱
When it come to my money,
我就像国庆日的烟火一样对[好]
I'm right as fireworks on the Fourth of July.
等着瞧
We gonna see.
你准备去提款吧!
You better get out your bank book!
他们在警局在说了什么? Gabe怎了?
What they say down there? What's happening with Gabe?
我过去接回他了, 花了我五十块
I went down there and got him out. Cost me $50.
说他在扰乱秩序
Said he was disturbing the peace.
法官三周后审讯
Judge set up a hearing for him in three weeks
他为何不被重新分配到医院内
to show cause why he shouldn't be recommitted.
那你怎说? 你怎跟法官说的
What'd you say? What'd you tell the judge?
我跟他说我会照顾他
I told him I'd take care of him.
没有理由又分配他住医院
It didn't make no sense to recommit the man.
他伸出他那贪婪的手
He stuck out his big greasy palm,
跟我说交出$50然后带他回家
told me to give him $50 and take him on home.
那他现在在哪?
Where's he at now? Where'd he go off to?
又到处乱跑了, 他不想别人拖着他的手
Gone about his business. He don't need nobody to hold his hand.
我也不知道, 但那看来是最好的选择
Well, I don't know, seem like that would be the best place for him.
让他住在医院里
To put him in a hospital.
我知道你接下来要说什么
I know what you say gonna say,
但那正是我认为这样做是对的原因
but that's what I think would be best.
那他在打仗时失去的一切, 为了什么?
Man had his life ruined fighting for what?
现在他们想把他锁起来?
Now, they want to take him and lock him up?
该给他自由啊, 他又没打扰谁
Let him be free. Man ain't bothering nobody.
我想每个人都有不同的看法
Everybody got their own way of looking at it, I guess.
来拿你的午餐吧
Come on, get your lunch.
我这里有些棉豆和玉米面包
I got some lima beans and cornbread in the oven.
快去, 你得吃点什么
Come on, get somethin' to eat.
在这里烦恼Gabe的事也没帮助
Ain't no sense in you fretting over Gabe.
Rose, 我有点事要跟你说
Rose, I got something to tell you.
- 待我把食物放好再说   - Rose...
- Wait till I put the food on the table. - Rose...
我不知道该怎开口
Now, I don't know how to tell you this.
但又不能瞒着你
And I can't explain it none.
[好感]就那么一点点的积聚啊
It just sort of grows on you.
开始时就像小木灌
It started off like a little bush,
待你发现时已经是整片森林了
next thing you know, it's a whole forest.
Troy, 你在说什么?
Troy, what is you talking about?
我在说话, 女人, 让我把话说完
I'm talking, woman. Let me talk.
我在跟你说
I'm trying to tell you,
我在找个隐晦的方法跟你说...
find a way to tell you that...
我要成为父亲了
I'm gonna be a daddy.
对, 我要成为别人的父亲了
Yeah, I'm gonna be somebody's daddy.
Troy, 不是真的吧? 你要成为什么?
Troy, you ain't telling me this. You're gonna be what?
- 你要成为别人的父亲?   - Rose...
- You're gonna be somebody's daddy?   - Rose...
你竟然跟你的妻子说这个?
You're telling your wife this?
现在...
Now...
嗨, Troy, 嗨, Rose
Hey, Troy! Hey, Rose!
我等了18年就为了听你说这些事吗?
I got to wait 18 years to hear something like this?
嗨, Rose
Hey, Rose.
我有朵花送给你
I got a flower for you.
那是朵玫瑰花, 就像你的名字一样
That's a rose. The same rose like you is.
谢了, Gabe
Thanks, Gabe.
Troy, 你没在生我的气吧?
Troy, you ain't mad at me?
那些坏人抓了我回来
Them bad mens come and put me away.
- 你没在生我的气吧?   - 没, 我没有生气
- You ain't mad at me?   - No. No, I ain't mad at you.
18年了, 你竟然做得出这种事?
Eighteen years, and you want to come with this?
看我拿到了什么? 一个全新的25美分
See what I got? Got a brand-new quarter.
Rose, 只是...
Rose, it's just that...
你没什么可以说, 也不用解释
Ain't nothing you can say, Troy. Ain't no explaining it.
给我这25美分的人还有一大堆
The fella that give me this quarter had a whole mess of 'em!
我要留着它直到它暗哑无光
I'm gonna keep this quarter till it stops shining.
Gabe, 出去前门等我, 我冰箱里有西瓜
Gabe, go on up front now.
I got some watermelon in the frigidaire.
快去, 我待会拿给你
Go on. I'll get you a piece.
Rose, 听我说, 我当时在追赶地狱之犬
Say, Rose, you know, I was chasing hellhounds,
然后那些坏人把我抓回去锁起来了
and them bad mens come and get me and take me away.
Troy救了我, 他来了并跟他们说
Troy helped me. He come down there and told them
他们最好在他打跨他们之前放了我
they better let me go before he beat them up!
他真的说了
Yeah, he did!
出去吧, Gabe, 我待会给你西瓜
Go up front now, Gabe. I'll get you some watermelon.
那些坏人都走了
Them bad men is gone now.
好吧, Rose要给我西瓜
Okay. Rose gonna give me some watermelon,
有条纹的那种
the kind with the stripes on it.
为什么, Troy?
Why, Troy?
为什么?
Why?
过了那么多年, 你现在跟我说这些?
After all these years, you come dragging this in to me now?
你这年纪, 不应该会做的
It don't make no sense at your age.
我可以理解你十年或者十五年前这样做, 但不是现在
I could've expected this 10, or 15 years ago, but not now.
年龄与此没有关系, Rose
Age ain't got nothing to do with it, Rose.
我做了一个妻子该做的
I done tried to be everything a wife should be.
一个妻子可以做的所有事
Everything a wife could be.
我结婚整整18年了
I've been married 18 years,
而现在竟到了你说
and now, I got to live to see the day you tell me
你和别的女人有了孩子的一天
you been seeing another woman and done fathered a child by her.
你明知道我不喜欢同父异母什么的
And you know I never wanted no half-nothing in my family!
我整个家庭都是这样
My whole family is half.
每个人都有不同的父母亲
Everybody got different fathers and mothers
我的几个兄弟姊妹都是这样
and my two sisters and my brothers.
你根本不知道谁是谁生的
You could hardly tell who's who.
永远不能好好谈谈父母的话题
Could never sit down and talk about papa and mama.
因为大家的父母都不一样
It was always your papa, your mama, my papa, my mama.
我从不想我的孩子们也是这样
And I ain't never wanted that for none of my children!
然而现在, 你竟然过来
And now, you want to drag your behind in here
跟我说这些事!
and tell me something like this!
够了, 你有权利知道的, 是时候了
Stop it now. You ought to know. It's time for you to know.
我才不想知道, 妈的!
Well, I don't want to know, god damn it!
Rose?
我不能让她堕胎, 米已成炊了
I just can't make it go away. It's done now.
我没法改变事情
I can't wish the circumstances of the thing away.
你也不想改变
And you don't want to, either.
或许你想我们两母子离开
Maybe you want to wish me and my boy away.
也许那就是你想的
Maybe that's what you want.
你不能这样做
Well, you can't wish us away.
我把我的18年放在你身上了
I got 18 years of my life invested in you.
你该留在我们的床上而不是出去鬼混
You ought to have stayed upstairs in my bed where you belong.
听着, 我们可以处理好这事
Now, listen to me. We can get a handle on this thing.
我们可以说清楚, 有共识
We can talk this out, come to an understanding.
突然间此事就是关于"我们"
All of a sudden it's "we."
当你在外面
Where was "we" at when
you were down there,
跟那个可恶的女人鬼混时"我们"在哪里?
rolling around with some godforsaken woman?
"我们"该在你做傻事之前
"We" should've come to an understanding
就要有共识!
before you started making a damn fool of yourself!
当说到共识时
You're a day late and a dollar short
你总是迟了
when it comes to an understanding with me.
Rose, 只是因为她能给我完全不同的感觉
Rose, it's just that she...gives me a different idea.
完全不同的自我理解
A different understanding about myself.
让我可以在这里走出去时, 放下所有压力
I can step out of this house and get away from the pressures
和问题, 变成一个完全不同的人
and the problems, be a different man.
我不用担心如何修好屋顶
I ain't got to worry about how I'll get the roof fixed,
或者付钱, 或者...
or pay the bills, or...
我可以
I can just
成为一个我前所未有过的自己
be a part of myself I ain't never been before.
我想知道的是...
What I want to know is...
我想知道的是
What I want to know
你是否打算继续见她?
is do you plan to continue seeing her?
那就是你可以说的
That's all you can say to me.
我在她的家里能放松下来
I could sit up in her house and laugh.
你明白吗?
You understand what I'm saying?
我可以放声笑, 而那感觉真好
I could laugh out loud, and it feels good.
简直好到了我心底里
It reaches all the way down to the bottom of my shoes.
Rose, 我...
Rose, I...
我不想放弃那些
I can't give that up.
那或许你该继续留在她那里
Well, maybe you ought to go on and stay down there with her,
如果她真是比我更好的女人的话
if she's a better woman than me.
这不是关于谁是更好的女人的问题
It ain't about nobody being a better woman, or nothing.
Rose, 你尽责了
Rose, you ain't to blame.
做妻子的话你简直是不二之选
A man couldn't ask for a better wife than you've been.
这事我得负起所有责任
I'm responsible for it.
我每天重复做着同样的事
I done locked myself into a pattern,
照顾你们, 都让我忘了自己了
trying to take care of you all, that I forgot about myself.
我不是一直在你背后吗?
Well, what the hell was I there for?
那是我的工作, 不是他人的
That was my job, not somebody else's.
Rose, 听着, 我竭尽所能去过正当的生活
Rose, listen to me. I done tried all my life to live decent.
一个正当, 努力向上的生活
To live a clean, hard, useful life.
我尽了力去成为一个好丈夫
I try to be a good husband to you, in every way I know how.
可能我一开始就错了吧, 我不知道
Maybe I come into the world backwards, I don't know,
但你就像上场前已经被二振了一样
but you're born with two strikes on you before you come to the plate.
你得把任何事都看管好
You got to guard it closely,
老是担心突发事情
always looking for the curveball on the inside corner.
你不能让任何事不受你控制
You can't afford a called strike.
你不能让任何事漏掉
You can't let nothing get past you.
要是你倒下了, 你还不死心
If you're going down, you're doing down swinging.
所有事都像对着你干一样
Everything lined up against you!
你还想怎样?
What you gonna do?
我赢了他们, Rose, 我短打了 [牺牲]
I fooled them, Rose. I bunted.
当我有你和Cory和份有点像样的工作, 我很安全
When I found you and Cory and a halfway decent job, I was safe.
没什么可以拖累我了
Couldn't nothing touch me!
我不会再被三振出局
I wasn't gonna strike out no more.
不会再回去坐牢
I wasn't going back to the penitentiary.
不会再喝醉, 睡在街上
I wasn't gonna lie in the street with a bottle of wine.
我安全了, 我有个家庭, 有份工作
I was safe. I had me a family, a job.
我不会被三振的
I wasn't gonna get that last strike.
我站在一垒
I was standing on first base,
等着回到本垒
waiting for one of them boys to
knock me in, to bring me home.
你该留在我们的床上, Troy
You should have stayed in my bed, Troy.
然后我看到那女子, 她让我胆大起来
Then I saw the gal, she firmed up my backbone.
我在想如果我努力点, 或许可以盗垒
I got to thinkin' that if I tried, maybe I could steal second.
- 你明白吗?   - 你该抱紧我
- You understand what I'm saying? - You should've held me tight.
你该捉紧我的手
You should've grabbed me and held on.
我站在一垒18年了
I stood on first base for 18 years,
然后我想, 管他的, 豁出去
and I thought, well, god damn it, go on for it!
我们不是在说棒球啊!
We ain't talking about baseball!
我们在说你跟别的女人鬼混
We talking about you going off and laying up with another woman,
然后把这事带回家跟我说
then bringing it home to me.
那才是我们要讨论的
That's what we're talking about.
- 我们不是要谈棒球!   - Rose, 你没细心听
- We're not talkin' about no baseball! - Rose, you're not listening to me.
我在用我最擅长的东西去表达
I'm trying to explain it to you the best way I know how.
对我来说很难去接受
It's not easy for me to admit
我站在原地18年了这事实
that I've been standing in the same place for 18 years!
我也跟你一起站在原地啊!
Well, I've been standing with you!
我一直都跟你站在原地, Troy! 我也有我的人生
I've been right here with you, Troy! I got a life, too.
我为此付出了我的18年啊
I gave 18 years of my life to stand in the same spot as you!
你没想过我也想要做其他事?
Don't you think I ever wanted other things?
没想过我也有我的梦想和愿望?
Don't you think I had dreams and hopes?
那我的生命呢? 那我呢?
What about my life? What about me?
你以为我没有想过
Don't you think it ever crossed my mind
去认识其他男人?
to want to know other men?
或者一走了之
That I wanted to lay up somewhere
忘了我的职责?
and forget about my responsibilities?
或者我想有过人让我笑
That I wanted someone to make me laugh,
让我快乐?
so I could feel good?
你不是唯一一个有需求的人
You're not the only one who's got wants and needs.
但我留下来了, Troy
But I held on to you, Troy.
我把我的所有情感, 需求和梦想
I took all my feelings, my wants and needs and dreams,
埋藏在你的心底下
and I buried them inside you.
我把种子埋藏好, 每天看着它, 祈望它成长
I planted a seed and watched and prayed over it.
我把自己埋藏在你心内然后等待开花!
I planted myself inside you and waited to bloom!
但那花了我18年时间
And it didn't take me no 18 years
才知道那泥土原来如石头般硬
to realize the soil was hard and rocky,
还有它根本不会开花!
and it wasn't never gonna bloom!
但我仍然捉紧你, 我把你捉得更紧
But I held on to you, Troy. I held you tighter.
你是我的丈夫
You was my husband.
我该给你我的全部
I owed you everything I had.
我的每一部分
Every part of me I could find to give you.
当晚上我在楼上的睡房时
And upstairs in that bedroom, with the darkness falling in on me,
我用尽力气消除那个疑虑
I gave everything I had to try and erase the doubt
那个其实你不是个好男人的疑虑
that you wasn't the finest man in the world.
无论你打算去哪里, 我都会跟着你
And wherever you was going, i was gonna be there with you,
因为你是我的丈夫
because you was my husband.
因为这样做我才能继续做你的妻子
'Cause that's the only way I was gonna survive as your wife.
你经常说给什么
You always talking about what you give
还有你不能给什么
and what you don't have to give.
但你也会拿取, Troy
But you take, too, Troy.
你会拿取而且不在乎是谁付出的
You take and don't even know nobody's giving.
你说我好逸恶劳
You say I take and don't give.
- Troy, 你弄痛我了   - 你说我好逸恶劳
- Troy, you're hurting me.   - You say I take and don't give.
- Troy, 我的手很痛, 放手!   - 我给了我能给的
- Troy, you're hurting my arm, let go!
- I gave you everything I got.
别说我没有
Don't you tell that lie on me.
- 妈妈!   - 别说我没有
- Mama!   - Don't you tell that lie!
Troy, 我弄痛我了!
Troy, you're hurting me!
Troy! Troy!
好了, 那是二振
All right. That's strike two.
你别再惹我, 你最好别三振
You stay away from around me, boy. Don't you strike out.
你满球数了
You're living with a full count.
你最好别三振!
Don't you strike out!
Troy, 我想跟你说点事
Troy, I want to talk to you.
突然间?
All of a sudden?
过了这么久你想跟我说点事?
After all this time, you want to talk to me, huh?
你数个月来没跟我说过一句话
You ain't wanted to talk to me in months.
昨晚也没有
You ain't wanted to talk to me last night.
你那时可不想理会我
You didn't want no parts of me then.
现在你想来说什么?
What you want to talk to me about now?
明天是星期五
Tomorrow's Friday.
我知道
I know what day tomorrow is.
你以为我不知道吗?
You think I don't know tomorrow's Friday?
我的整生, 都在等星期五的来临
My whole life, I ain't done nothing but look to see Friday coming,
你还来提醒我
and you got to tell me it's Friday.
我想知道你会否回家
I want to know if you're coming home.
我每天都回家, 你知道的
I always come home, Rose. You know that.
没有一晚我是没回来的
Ain't never been a night I ain't come home.
你明知道那不是我的意思
That ain't what I mean, and you know it.
我想知道你下班后会否直接回家
I wanna know if you're coming straight home after work.
我想我会兑换支票, 然后在Taylor的酒吧和他们喝点酒
I figured I'd cash my check,
hang out at Taylors' with the boys.
或许玩一局[西洋]跳棋
Maybe play a game of checkers.
Troy, 我不能再继续这样, 我接受不了
Troy, I can't live like this. I won't live like this.
自那之后你就人在心不在
You're living on borrowed time with me.
六个月以来, 你都没真正回来
Been going on six months now, you ain't been coming home.
我每晚都回来, 一年来从没间断过
I come home every night. Every night of the year.
那就整整365天
That's 365 days.
我想你明天下班后直接回家
I want you to come home tomorrow after work.
Rose, 你知道我不会乱花钱
Rose, I don't mess up my pay. You know that.
我收到工资后就全数交给你
I take my pay, i give it to you.
我只拿着你分配给我的部份
I don't have no money but what you give me back.
我只想要一点私人时间而已
I just want a little time to myself.
去享乐一下
A little time to enjoy life.
那我呢? 何时才轮到我去享乐?
What about me? When's my time to enjoy life?
我不知道还可以说什么, 我已经尽力了
I don't know what to tell you, Rose. I'm doing the best I can.
你下班回家后
You ain't been comin' home from work,
只换件衣服又出去了
but time enough to change your clothes and run out.
你叫那尽力吗?
You wanna call that the best you can do?
我晚点得去医院看Alberta
I'm going over to the hospital to see Alberta.
她今天下午进了医院
She went into the hospital this afternoon.
看来是早产
Looks like she might have the baby early.
我不会去太久
I won't be gone long.
你该知道他们今天到了Pearl小姐那里
Well, you ought to know. They went over to Miss Pearl's
带走了Gabe
and got Gabe today.
她说你叫他们锁起他来
She said you told them to go ahead and lock him up.
我才没有说过, 你被她骗了
I ain't said no such thing. Whoever told you that is telling a lie.
Pearl小姐撒了个很大的谎
Miss Pearl ain't doing nothing but telling a big, fat lie.
她不用说出口, 我在文件上看到的
She ain't had to tell me. I read it on the papers.
- 那份文件说了什么?   - 说你叫他们去带走他
- What'd it say, huh?   - It said you told them to take him.
那他们肯定弄错了
Oh, well, then they screwed that up,
就像他们弄错其他事一样
just like they screw up everything.
我才不在意他们在文件上说了什么
I ain't worried about what they got on that paper.
说政府会把他的部分财产交给医院作照顾费用
It say the government sends part of the check to the hospital,
另一部份交给你
the other part to you.
我跟此事毫无关系
I ain't got nothing to do with that, if that's the way it works.
我也没叫他们分给我
I don't make up the rules...
你对待Gabe就像你对待Cory一样差劲
You did Gabe just like you did Cory.
你不会替Cory签署
You wouldn't sign the paper for Cory,
但你却替Gabe签了, 是你签的!
but you signed for Gabe! You signed that paper!
我说过我没有签署过什么, 女人
I told you I ain't signed nothing, woman.
天啊, 我只签了份释放同意书
Hell, the only thing I signed was the release form.
我又不识字
Hell, I can't read,
天知道他们在同意书上写了什么
I don't know what they had on that paper.
我才没签过什么送走Gabe的文件
I ain't signed nothing about sending Gabe away.
我当时说送他到医院, 你说要让他自由
I said send him to the hospital, you said let him go free.
现在你反过来
Then you went down there
同意送他到医院, 就为了他的钱
and you signed him to the hospital for half his money.
这是自相矛盾, Troy
You went back on yourself, Troy.
你会有报应的
You're gonna have to answer for that.
你才跟Pearl小姐说过话
You just been over there talking to Miss Pearl.
她只是因为不能再
She just mad 'cause she ain't gettin'
骗Gabe的钱而生气, 所以胡说而已
Gabe's rent money, that's all it is.
Troy, 我亲眼看着你签的!
Troy, I seen where you signed the paper!
你才没有!
You ain't seen nothing I signed!
那她家里为何又有我弟弟的文件?
And what she doing got papers on my brother for, anyway?
Pearl小姐只是在撒谎
Miss Pearl ain't doing nothing but telling a big, fat lie,
我会去跟她对质!
and I'm gonna tell her about it, too!
我没有签署过什么!
You ain't seen nothing I signed!
还说我...
Say...
我没有签署过什么!
You ain't seen nothing I signed!
Troy.
那是医院打来说Alberta生下来了
That was the hospital. Alberta had the baby.
是吗? 是男还是女的?
Yeah? What she have? What is it?
是个女孩
It's a girl.
我...
I...
我该去看她一下
I better get on down there to see her.
Troy.
- Troy   - 我总得去看她一下吧, Rose
- Troy. - I got to go see her now, Rose. That's only right.
怎么了? 婴儿什么有问题吗?
What's the matter? Baby all right, ain't it?
Alberta产后死去了
Alberta died having the baby.
你说她死了?
She died? You say she's dead?
她死了?
Alberta dead?
他们说尽了力, 他们...
They said they done all they could. They...
他们对她无能为力
They couldn't do nothing for her.
那婴儿呢? 她还好吗?
Oh, what about the baby? Baby all right?
他们说她很健康
They say it's healthy.
我在想谁会替她办身后事
I wonder who's gonna bury her.
她有家人的, Rose
She had a family, Rose.
她不是无亲无故
She wasn't living in the world by herself.
我当然知道
I know she wasn't living in the world by herself.
你下一样想知道的就是她有没有保险
Next thing you wanna know if she had any insurance.
你没资格跟我这样说话!
You ain't got to talk to me like that!
你第一样关心的就是: 谁会埋葬她?
First thing that jumped out your mouth. "Who's gonna bury her?"
生怕我会付钱替她办理
Like I'm finna take that task on for myself.
我是你的妻子, 别推开我
I'm your wife. Don't push me away.
我没有推开谁, 就给我点空间
I ain't pushing nobody away. Just give me some space.
让我静一下
Just give me some room to breathe.
好了, 死神先生
All right, Mr. Death.
我来告诉你接下来的事
I tell you what I'm gonna do.
我会继续
I'm gonna take
在这后院筑起籓篱, 知道吗?
and build me a fence around this yard, see?
我会筑起籓篱保护属于我的东西
I'm gonna build me a fence around what belongs to me.
然后我想你留在另一边
And then I want you to stay on the other side.
直至你准备好带走我
You stay over there till you're ready for me,
到时候你就尽管来吧
then you come on.
带上你的军队, 镰刀, 披上你的袍子
Bring your army, bring your sickle, bring your wrestling clothes.
这次我不会松懈
I ain't gonna fall down on my vigilance this time.
你不会...
You ain't gonna...
你不会就有机可乘
You ain't gonna sneak up on me no more.
当你准备好时
When you ready for me,
当你手上的名单写着Troy Maxson时
when the top of your list say Troy Maxson,
到时候你就正面而来吧
then you come on up and knock on the front door.
其他人与此无关
Ain't nobody else got nothing to do with this.
这是你我之间的事
This between you and me.
男人之间!
Man to man!
你在准备好带走我之前留在籓篱的另一边!
You stay on the other side of that fence till you ready for me!
然后随时都可以
Then you come up and knock on that front door
与我正面对决!
anytime you want!
我拭目以待
I'll be ready for you.
Rose?
我在抱着我的女孩
I'm standing here with my daughter in my arms.
听着
Now,
她只不过是一个
she ain't but a wee,
初生的婴儿而已
bitty little old thing.
她跟大人间的事没有关系
She don't know nothing about grownfolk business.
她是无辜的
She innocent,
但她没有母亲
and she ain't got no mama.
你为何告诉我这些, Troy?
What you telling me for, Troy?
那...
Well...
我们在外面门廊好了
Guess we'll go sit out here on the porch.
一个男人应该做他认为正确的事
A man's got to do what's right for him.
我毫不后悔我做过的事
I ain't sorry for nothing I done.
我内心感到那是对的事
It felt right in my heart.
小宝宝在笑什么?
What you smiling at?
你父亲是个年纪老迈的好人
Your daddy's a great, big ol' man.
无所畏惧, 但有时候也难免会害怕
Got these great big ol' hands, but sometimes he's scared.
而现在你父亲正正在害怕
And right now, your daddy's scared 'cause we
因为我们只能在这门廊坐着, 无家可归
sitting out here on the porch and ain't got no home.
我也试过居无定所
Oh, I've been homeless before.
但我没试过带着婴儿无家可归
I ain't never had no baby with me, but I've been homeless.
就只是寂寞的在外面流连
You just be out there on the road by your lonesome
看着列车一架一架
and just see one of them trains coming by
来了又走...
and just kinda go, say...
她是我的女儿, Rose, 是我的...
She's my daughter, Rose, and my...
我的亲生骨肉, 我不能遗弃她
My own flesh and blood. I can't deny her.
就像我不能遗弃我的儿子们
No more than I can deny them boys.
你们几母子都是我的家人
You and them boys is my family.
你们, 还有这孩子就是我唯一拥有的, 所以...
You, them, and this child is all I got in this world, so...
我想我要说的是
I guess what I'm saying is,
如果你能替我照顾她, 我会很感谢你
that I'd appreciate it if you was to help me take care of her.
好吧, Troy
Okay, Troy,
你是对的
you're right.
我会替你照顾你的孩子
I'll take care of your baby for you.
因为如你所说
'Cause, like you say,
她是无辜的
she innocent.
总不能把父亲的罪名降到孩子身上
You can't visit the sins of the father upon the child.
况且单亲孩子的日子会很艰难
Motherless child's got a hard time.
从今起, 这孩子有个母亲了
From right now, this child's got a mother.
但你是个寡夫
But you're a womanless man.
大家都避开我
I'm coming in, everybody going out.
我得带这蛋糕到教堂的蛋糕义卖
I'm taking this cake down to the church for the bake sale.
Lyons刚来过看你, 想要还你的二十块
Lyons was by to see you. He stopped by to pay you your $20.
钱就在桌上
It's laying right here on the table.
拿着, 是我的工资
Well, here go this money.
放在桌上吧, Troy, 我晚点处理
Well, put it in there on the table, Troy. I'll get it.
你什么时候回来?
What time you coming back?
你在这里问东问西也没用
Ain't no use in you studyin' me.
我何时回来也没关系
Don't matter what time I come back.
我只是问一下而已, 女人, 现在都不给问了吗?
I just asked you a question, woman. Can't I ask you a question?
Troy, 我不想吵架
Troy, I don't want to get into it.
你的餐在炉子里
Now, your food is in there on the stove.
翻热一下就好了
All you got to do is heat it up.
还有别吃掉蛋糕
And don't be eating the rest of them cakes in there now.
我还得用
I'm coming back for them.
明天下午也有蛋糕义卖
We're having a bake sale at the church tomorrow.
[工资]
嗨, Troy
Hey, Troy.
怎了, Bono?
What's happening, Bono?
只是想来看看你
I just thought I'd stop by to see you.
你家里没人, 所以我猜...
Wasn't no one at the house, so I figured...
为什么?
What you stop by to see me for?
你很久没来看我了
You ain't stopped by in a month of Sundays.
天啊, 我肯定欠了你钱还是什么的
Hell, I must owe you some money or somethin'.
你还说, 自从你升职后我都快跟不上你了
Well, since you got your promotion, I can't keep up with you.
以前早晚都看到你
Used to see you every day.
现在我甚至不知道你在哪工作
Now I don't even know what route you working.
他们老是调配我到不同地方工作
Keep switching me around.
现在我负责白人的街区
Got me out there in green tree now, hauling white folk garbage.
- 白人街区吗?   - 对
- Green tree, huh?   - Yeah.
你真幸运
You lucky.
至少你不用搬垃圾
At least you ain't got to be lifting them barrels.
该死的, 它们越来越重
Damn if they ain't getting heavier.
我再多工作两年就退休了
I'm gonna put in my two years and call it quits.
对, 我也在想退休的事
Yeah, I'm thinking about retiring myself.
你的工作轻松多了
Oh, you got it easy.
你可以再多驾驶五年啊
You could drive for another five years.
那可不同, Bono
Ain't the same, Bono.
驾驶不像搬垃圾
It ain't like working the back of the truck.
只能独自工作, 没人聊天
You feel like you working by yourself. Ain't nobody to talk to.
不了, 还是退休吧, Lucille最近怎样?
Naw, I'm thinking about retiring. How's Lucille?
她很好
She all right.
她的关节炎有时候会复发
Her arthritis get to acting up on her sometimes.
我过来时看到Rose, 她在教堂吗?
Saw Rose on the way here. She going down to the church, huh?
对, 她过去了
Yeah, she took up going down there.
那些传教士只想捞油水而已
All them preachers looking to fatten their pockets.
这里有琴酒
Got some gin in here.
不了谢谢, 我只是来看看你
No, thanks. I just stopped in to say hello.
你也可以喝一杯啊朋友, 我从没...
Well, you can take a drink, nigger. I ain't...
认识你以来从没看过你不喝酒
I ain't never known you to say no to a drink.
你明天又不用上班
You ain't got to work tomorrow.
我只是来一下而已
I just stopped by.
我在想晚点到Skinner家里
I'm thinkin' of going over to Skinner's.
我们每星期五都会在他家里玩多米诺骨牌
We got us a domino game going over his house every Friday.
朋友, 你才不会玩什么多米诺骨牌
Nigger, you can't play no dominoes.
我以前老是赢你
I used to whup you four games out of five.
我吸取了教训, 我玩牌的技术在进步
Well, that learned me. I'm getting better.
是吗?
Yeah?
好吧
That's all right.
我得走了
Look here, I got to be getting on.
有空来找我一下?
Stop by sometime, huh?
我会的, Bono
Yeah, I'll do that, Bono.
Lucille跟Rose说你给她买了个新冰箱
Lucille told Rose you, uh, got her that new refrigerator.
对啊, Rose跟Lucille说你终于把籓篱建好了
Yeah. Rose told Lucille you had finally built your fence,
所以我想我们就扯平了
so, I figured we'd call it even.
我就知道你信守承诺
I knew you would.
是啊
Yeah.
好了
Okay.
再见
I'll be talking to you.
很高兴看到你, Bono
Yeah, good to see you, Bono.
我有空会来找你的
I'm gonna stop over.
好吧, Troy
Yeah. Okay, Troy.
[美国海军陆战队招募署]
我要进去
I got to get by.
你说什么?
Say what? What you say?
你挡着我了, 我得进去
You in my way. I got to get by.
你得去哪?
You got to get by where?
这是我付钱买的房子
This is my house. Bought and paid for.
花了我15年之久, 如果你想进我的房子
Took me 15 years, and if you want to go in my house
而我坐在家门楼梯上的话, 你该说"请让一下"
and I'm sitting on the steps, you say, "excuse me,"
就像你妈妈教你那样
like your mama taught you.
得了吧, 爸, 我得进去
Come on, pop, I gotta get by.
你想就这样无视我?
You just gonna walk over the top of me?
我也在这里住的
I live here, too.
你想在我的地方无视我?
You just gonna walk over the top of me in my own house?
我不怕你
I ain't scared of you.
我没在问你是否害怕我
I ain't asked you if you was scared of me.
我是问你是否要在
I asked you was you finna walk over the top of me
我的地方无视我? 那才是我问的
in my own house? That was the question.
你不会说"请让一下"
You ain't gonna say, "excuse me."
你就这样无视我
You just gonna walk over the top of me.
随便你怎说
If you want to put it like that.
我怎说了?
How else am I gonna put it?
我是想绕过你进去
I was walking by you to go into the house,
因为你醉了, 在楼梯上唱歌
'cause you sitting on the steps drunk, singing to yourself.
- 你也可以这样说   - 也不说"请让一下"?
- You can put it like that.   - Without saying, "excuse me"?
我问你了, 也不说"请让一下"?
I asked you a question. Without saying, "excuse me"?
我不用对你客气
I ain't got to say "excuse me" to you.
你在这个家里不重要了
You don't count around here no more.
我懂了, 我在这里不重要了
Oh, I see. I don't count around here no more.
你也不用跟你的父亲客气了
You ain't got to say "excuse me" to your daddy.
突然间, 你就可以作主
All of a sudden, you done got so grown,
认为你父亲在这里不重要对吧?
where your daddy don't count around here no more, huh?
在他辛劳工作才得以
Around here in his own house and yard
买回来的地方吗?
that he done paid for with the sweat of his brow?
突然间, 你就可以作主
All of a sudden, you done got so grown
认为你父亲在这里毫无地位
that your daddy don't even count around here.
你要成为一家之主吗?
What, you gonna take over?
你要接管我的屋子吗? 你要拿走我的东西吗?
You gonna take over my house? You gonna wear my pants?
你要睡在我的床上吗?
You gonna go in there and stretch out on my bed?
你认为你不用再对你父亲客气
You ain't got to say, "excuse me,"
因为他在这里毫无地位
because your daddy don't count around here no more.
- 对吗?   - 正是
- Is that right?   - That's right.
你老是说这种蠢事
You always talking this dumb stuff.
为何不放过我一下?
Now why don't you just get out my way?
我猜你有自己的房子了
I guess you got some place to sleep.
也能够养活自己, 你能吗?
Something to put in your belly. You got that?
因为那就是你需要做到的, 你能吗?
'Cause that's what you need. You got that?
你不知道我有什么能耐! 你也没有权利过问!
You don't know what I got! You ain't got to worry about what I got!
你说得对
You right.
完全正确
You 100% right.
十七年来我一直都照顾你, 担心你
I done spent the last 17 years worrying about what you got.
所以现在轮到你作主了吗?
Now, it's your turn, see?
我跟你说清楚现在的情况
I tell you what we do.
你长大了, 我们都知道吧
You grown. We done established that.
你说你是成人, 现在就看看你到底是不是
You a man. Now, let's see you act like one.
你现在转身离开这里
Turn your behind around and walk out this yard.
当你走出巷子时
And when you get out there in the alley,
你把这间屋子抛诸脑后
you can forget about this house, see.
因为这是我的房子
'Cause this is my house.
你出去, 成为你所谓的大人, 然后找个地方住
You go on and be a man and get your own house.
你可以把这一切忘掉, 因为这都是我的
You can forget about this, 'cause this is mine.
你出去过你的生活, 因为我已经不想再为你做什么了
You go on and get yours, 'cause I'm through doing for you.
还扯为我做的事, 你给过我什么?
What you done for me. What you ever give me?
你的身体, 那个还在跳动的心脏, 臭小子
Them feet. Them bones. That pumping heart, nigger!
我比任何人给过你的都多
Give you more than anybody else ever gonna give you.
你才没有给过我什么!
You ain't never gave me nothing!
你只会拖累我
You ain't never done nothing but hold me back,
害怕我会比你有成就!
afraid I was gonna be better than you!
你做过的所有只是想让我害怕你
All you ever did was try and make me scared of you.
以前你每一次叫我的时候, 我都在颤抖
I used to tremble every time you called my name.
每一次我在屋里听到你的脚步声也是
Every time I heard your footsteps in this house.
总是在想: 如果我这样做, 爸怎样反应?
Wondering all the time, "what's pop gonna say if I do this?
他又会怎样说?
"What's he gonna say if I do that?
如果我打开收音机他又会怎说?
"What's pop gonna say if I turn on the radio?"
妈妈也是! 她试着不去害怕你, 但终究也没用
And mom, too! She tries, but she's scared of you.
你妈妈与此无关, 她...
Leave your mama out of
this. Your mama ain't got...
真不懂为何你这样对她后, 她还能接受你
I don't know how she stands you after what you did to her!
我说过, 别把你妈妈混进这事
I told you, leave your mama outta this.
你要怎样做? 打我吗?
What are you gonna do? Give me a whupping?
你不能再打我了! 你太老了
You can't whup me no more! You're too old!
你只是个老头而已
You're just an old man.
臭小子!
Nigger!
你就是这样, 只是个...
That's what you are. You're just...
对我来说你只是个街上的流氓而已
You're just another nigger on the street to me.
你疯了! 你知道吗?
You're crazy! You know that?
对, 去吧
Yeah, go on.
就这样无视我, 你骨子里头是个恶人
Get on away from around me. You got the devil in you.
你只是个疯老头! 还说我是恶人
You are just a crazy old man! Talkin' about I got the "devil" in me!
对, 我疯了
Yeah. I am crazy.
如果你不滚出我的院子
If you don't get the hell out of my yard,
我会让你看看我有多疯
I'm gonna show you how crazy I am.
快滚出我的院子!
Now, go on, get the hell out of my yard!
这不是你的院子!
This ain't your yard!
你拿了Gabe叔叔打仗后的赔偿
You took Uncle Gabe's money he got from the army
去买这间房子, 然后赶走他了
to buy this house, when you put him out!
快滚出我的院子
Get your black ass out of my yard!
我哪都不去!
I ain't going nowhere!
来啊, 赶走我啊, 我才不怕你
Come on, put me out, i ain't scared of you.
- 那是我的球棒   - 来啊
- That's my bat.   - Come on.
- 放下我的球棒   - 来啊, 赶走我!
- Put my bat down.   - Come on, put me out!
怎么了? 你要是那么棒, 赶走我啊!
What's the matter? You so bad. Put me out!
你要有用它的打算
You're gonna have to use it.
你敢对着我拿起球棒, 就要有用它的打算
You want to draw that bat back on me, you're gonna have to use it.
来啊!
Come on!
你要有打死我的打算
You're gonna have to kill me.
要是你敢对着我拿起球棒
You want to draw that bat back on me,
你就要有打死我的打算
you're gonna have to kill me.
来啊
Come on.
你过来, 我教你
Come on. Then I'll show you.
来啊!
Come on!
走吧, 别再在我的房子出现
Go on, get away from around my house.
走啊
Go on.
跟妈妈说我会回来收拾细软
Tell mama I'll be back for my things.
你的东西会被扔出这藩篱外!
They'll be on the other side of that fence!
感受不到
Can't taste nothing.
我什么都感受不到
I can't taste nothing.
哈利路亚
Hallelujah!
Hallelujah.
哈利路亚
我什么都感受不到了
I can't taste nothing no more.
来吧
Come on.
你和我作个了断吧
It's between you and me now.
来吧, 随时都行
Come on. Anytime you want.
来吧, 我准备好了
Come on. I be ready for you.
但你别想能全身而退
But I ain't gonna be easy.
Raynell?
- 夫人?   - 你在做什么?
- Ma'am?   - What you doing?
没什么
Nothing.
进来换衣服吧, 你在做什么?
Get in here and get dressed. What are you doing?
看看它们有没有长大
See if my garden growed.
我说过它们不会一晚就长大
I told you it ain't gonna grow overnight.
你得耐心点
You got to wait.
对, 但那看起好像永远不会长大, 该死的!
Yeah, but it look like it ain't never gonna grow, mama. Dag!
我说过, 心急水不沸
I told you, a watched pot never boils.
那可不同, 妈妈
This ain't even no pot, mama.
进来换衣服
Get in here and get dressed.
这不是出外玩的时候, 听到了吗?
This ain't no morning to be playing around, you hear me?
明白, 夫人
Yes, ma'am.
再见, 小田园
Bye, garden.
你好, 你想必就是Raynell吧
Hi. I bet your name is Raynell.
你妈妈在家吗?
Is your mama home?
妈妈, 有个男人找你!
Mama, there's a man down here!
妈妈
Mama!
Cory?
Cory.
Cory, Cory!
Cory. Cory!
- 噢, 我主慈悲!   - Cory
- Oh! Lord have mercy!   - Cory.
你们看看谁来了
Lookee here, y'all.
看他啊
Aww, looka here.
都长大了
Done got all grown up.
别哭, 妈妈, 为何要哭呢?
Don't cry, mama. What you crying about?
只是因为你出现了
I'm just so glad you made it.
嗨, Lyons, 你最近怎了, Bono先生?
Hey, Lyons. How you doing, Mr. Bono?
看看你啊, 老兄
Look at you, man, look at you.
他看上去很威风凛凛吧, Rose? 都是下士了
Don't he look good, Rose? Got on them corporal stripes.
为何现在才来?
What took you so long?
你知道军队怎操作的吧, 妈妈
You know how the marines are, mama.
他们得把所有文件检查清楚
They got to get all their paperwork straight
才让你做任何事
before they let you do anything.
怎样都好, 我很高兴你赶来了, 他们让Lyons来
Well, I'm sure glad you made it. They let Lyons come.
你的叔叔Gabe还在医院内
Your Uncle Gabe's still in the hospital.
他们不知道该否让他出来
They don't know if they're gonna let him out or not.
我刚跟他们说过话
I talked to them a little while ago.
美国海军陆战队的下士
A corporal in the United States marines.
你爸爸早知道你是军人的材料
Your daddy knew you had it in you.
他以前总是这样告诉我
He used to tell me all the time.
他看上去很不错吧, Bono先生?
Hey, don't he look good, Mr. Bono?
对, 他让我记起我第一次见到的Troy
Yeah, he reminds me of Troy when I first met him.
我说, Rose
Ah, say, Rose,
Lucille现在在教堂和唱诗班一起
Lucille's down at the church with the choir.
我先去跟那些护柩者说一下
I'm gonna go get the pallbearers lined up.
晚点回来
I'll be back to get you all.
谢谢, Jim
Thanks, Jim.
晚点见, Bono先生
See you, Mr. Bono.
Cory, 看看Raynell
Cory, look at Raynell.
不是很美吗?
Ain't she precious?
她将来定是个大美人
She's gonna break a whole lot of hearts.
跟你的哥哥打招呼, 这是你的哥哥Cory
Say hello to your brother. This your brother, Cory.
你记得Cory吗?
You remember Cory?
不记得, 夫人
No, ma'am.
她怎可能记得我, 妈妈
Naw, she don't remember me, mama.
我们有时候会说起你, 她也在的
Oh, well, we talk about you. She heard us talk about you.
这是你的哥哥Cory, 快打招呼
This is your brother, Cory. Say hello.
- 你好   - 你好
- Hi.   - Hi.
所以你就是Raynell吧
So, you're Raynell.
妈妈说了很多关于你的事给我
Mama's told me a lot about you.
让我煮点早餐给你吃, 别饿坏
Come on, let me fix you some breakfast. Keep up your strength.
我不饿, 妈妈
I ain't hungry, mama.
你可以煮点什么给我, 我待会进去找你
You can fix me something, Rose. I'll be in there in a minute.
你确定不吃点什么吗, Cory?
You sure you don't want nothing, Cory?
我知道他们没什么好吃的给你
I know they ain't feeding you right.
不了, 妈妈, 谢谢, 我现在不想吃
No, mama, thanks. I don't feel like eating.
晚点吧
I'll get something later.
Raynell, get up there and get
that dress on like I told you.
我早就知道你能成就大事
I always knew you was gonna make something out of yourself.
你永远朝着正确的方向走
Your head was always in the right direction.
所以
So,
你打算继续服役吗?
you gonna stay in?
让它成为你的事业? 为军队付出20年?
Make it a career? Put in your 20 years?
我不知道, 已经服役六年了, 我想已经足够了
I don't know. I got six already. I think that's enough.
为美国效力然后早早退休
Stick with Uncle Sam and retire early.
这里没有什么
Ain't nothing out here.
我想Rose跟你说过我发生什么事了吧
I guess Rose told you about what happened with me.
他们现在让我在囚犯工厂工作
They got me down at the workhouse.
我自以为偷偷的兑现他人支票很聪明
I thought I was being slick cashing other people's checks.
被判多少年了?
How much time you doing?
三年
They give me three years.
我接受了, 现在只剩九个月
I got that beat now. I ain't got but nine more months.
那也不是件坏事
It ain't so bad.
你能学会如何面对它, 像面对其他事一样
You learn to deal with it like anything else.
人生不如意事十常八九
"You got to take the crookeds with the straights,"
那就是爸爸的座右铭
that's what papa used to say.
他以前被三振后老是这样说
He used to say that when he struck out.
我看见过他被连续三次三振
I seen him strike out three times in a row,
再上场时, 他把球打到看台上
and the next time up, he hit the ball over the grandstand.
在霍姆斯特德的棒球场上 [佛罗里达州]
Right out there in Homestead field.
他打到看台上还不满意
He wasn't satisfied hitting in the seats.
他想打出球场外
He wanted to hit it over everything.
比赛完结后
Then after the game,
有200位观众等着与他握手
he had 200 people standing around, waiting to shake his hand.
人生不如意事十常八九
You got to take the crookeds with the straights.
他真与众不同
Papa was something else.
你还在玩音乐吗?
You still playing?
Cory, 你知道我不会放弃音乐的
Cory, you know I'm gonna do that.
我跟那里几个志同道合的人, 组成了乐队
We got some fellas down there. We got us a band.
出狱后我们打算继续一起表演, 但...
We gonna try to stay together when we get out, but...
对
Yeah.
我还在玩音乐
I'm still playing.
它仍然是我有动力活下去的原因
Still helps me get out of bed in the morning.
只要它一天是
As long as it do that,
我就不会放弃它, 更认真对待它
I'm gonna stick with it, try to make some sense out of it.
Lyons, 我煮了蛋给你
Lyons, I got these eggs in a pan.
让我进去吃点什么, 老兄
Let me get in here and get these eggs, man.
然后准备让爸爸入土
Get ready to go bury papa.
你过得怎样了?
How you doing?
你还好吗?
You doing all right?
你好
Hi.
你以前睡在我的房间吗?
You used to sleep in my room?
对, 那以前是我的房间
Yeah, that used to be my room.
那就是爸爸说的, Cory的房间
That's what papa callit. "Cory's room."
你的美式足球还在柜里
Got your football in the closet.
Raynell, 快换衣服, 也穿上新的鞋子
Raynell. Get up there, get dressed, and put them good shoes on.
妈妈, 我就不能穿这双吗? 那双新鞋子弄痛我的脚
Mama, can I just wear these? Them others hurt my feet!
那也只会弄痛一会儿而已
Well, they're just gonna have to hurt your feet for a while.
你买的时候
You ain't said they hurt your feet
也没说它们会弄痛你
when you went down to the store and got 'em.
那时候不痛, 现在我的双脚都长大了
They didn't hurt then. My feet done got bigger.
别给我顶嘴!
Don't give me no back talk!
快换衣服, 穿上新鞋子
Get up there, get dressed, and put them good shoes on.
这里没什么大改变
Ain't too much changed.
那棒球还吊在树上
He still got that rag tied to the tree.
他当时在这里挥棒
He was out here swinging that bat.
我刚想回去屋子内
I was just getting ready to go back in the house.
他一挥, 然后整个人就倒下了
He swung that bat and just fell over.
当他挥棒时, 他看起来好像在笑
Seem like, when he swung it, he stood there with this grin on his face.
下一秒就倒下了
Then he just fell over.
他们来把他送到医院
They carried him down there to the hospital,
但我知道已经没有需要了
but I knew there wasn't no need.
不如跟我进去再说?
Why don't you come on in the house?
妈妈, 我有点事要告诉你
Mama, I got something to tell you.
我不知道该怎开口, 但我得告诉你
I don't know how to tell you this, but I got to tell you.
我不会出席爸爸的葬礼
I'm not going to papa's funeral.
小子, 闭嘴
Boy, hush your mouth.
那是你的爸爸!
That's your daddy you talking about!
我不想在这种时候听到你说这个
I don't want to hear that kind of talk this morning.
我这么辛苦把你养成这样的吗?
I done raised you to come to this?
你健健康康的
You standing there all healthy and grown,
怎么说你不出席爸爸的葬礼了?
talking about you ain't going to your daddy's funeral?
- 妈妈, 听着   - 我不想听, Cory!
- Mama, listen... - I don't want to hear it, Cory!
别再改样想了
Just get that thought out of your head.
我得向他说不, 就一次, 我得说不
I've got to say no to him. One time in my life, I got to say no.
我不想听这些!
I don't got to listen to that!
我知道你和你爸爸不和
Now, I know you and your daddy ain't seen eye to eye,
但我不想在这种时候听到你说出这种话
but I don't have to listen to that kind of talk this morning.
不尊重父亲不是作为一个男人该做的事, Cory
Disrespecting your daddy ain't gonna make you a man, Cory.
你得找个方法让自己接受
You gotta find some way to come to that on your own.
不出席你爸爸的葬礼不会让你成人的
Not going to your daddy's funeral ain't gonna make you a man.
我以前在这里的日子
The whole time I was growing up, living in his house,
爸爸就像一道永远跟着你的黑影
papa was like a shadow that followed you everywhere.
它就像个重担, 它会侵蚀到你体内
It weighed on you, and it sunk into your flesh.
它会把你紧紧的包着, 不让你走
It would wrap around you and lay there
直到你分不清哪个才是真正的自己
until you couldn't tell which one was you anymore.
那黑影就一点点的侵蚀到你皮下
That shadow just diggin' into your flesh!
试着占据你的心, 然后控制你
Trying to crawl in. Trying to live through you.
哪里都是Troy Maxson的踪影
Everywhere I looked, I saw Troy Maxson staring right back at me.
在你床下, 又或是在衣柜内
Hiding under the bed, in the closet.
我只是想说我得找个方法
I'm just saying I got to find a way
去摆脱那个黑影, 妈妈
to get rid of that shadow, mama.
你就像他, 他早已占据你的心了
You just like him. You got him in you good.
别说我是他, 妈妈
Don't tell me that, mama.
你简直就是Troy Maxson
You Troy Maxson all over again.
我不想成为Troy Maxson!
I don't want to be Troy Maxson!
我只想做我自己
I just want to be me.
你永远都会是你自己啊, Cory
You can't be nobody but who you are, Cory.
那黑影只不过是你自己制造出来的
That shadow wasn't nothing but you growing into yourself.
你要么早晚成为它, 要么就只接受它的部份
You either got to grow into it, or cut it down to fit you,
但你要生活就得这样做
but that's all you got to make a life with.
那就是唯一你要跟外面的人比较的东西
That's all you got to measure yourself against the world out there.
你爸爸想你成为和他完全不一样的人
Your daddy wanted you to be everything he wasn't,
同时间
and at the same time,
他也想你成为他啊
he wanted you to be everything he was.
我不评论他是对还是错
Now, I don't know if he was right or wrong,
但我知道
but I do know
他本意是想做好事而非伤害你
he meant to do more good than he meant to do harm.
有时候他想碰触他人, 自己也会受伤
Sometimes, when he touched, he bruised,
有时候他想做好事, 却成了坏事
and sometimes, when he took me in his arms, he cut.
我最初遇见你爸爸时
When I first met your daddy,
我在想
I thought,
那是个我可以付托终身的人
"here is a man I can lay down with and make a baby."
那就是我对他的第一个想法
That's the first thing I thought when I seen him.
我当时想: Rose Lee
I thought, "Rose Lee,
那是个你可以真诚相对的人
"here's a man you can open yourself up to
然后被他的爱填得满满的
"and be filled to bursting!
那是个可以把你心里空白的位置
"Here's a man that can fill up all them empty spaces
全都补上的人
"you been tipping around the edges of."
当你爸爸进门时
When your daddy walked through the house,
他是...
he was just
那么的大啊 [形容他独力承担起家庭]
so big.
他心里全都占满了 [工作]
He filled it up!
那是我犯下的第一个错误
That was my first mistake.
没让他在心里留点位置给我
Not to make him leave some room for me.
但
But
我想要个快乐的家
I wanted a house I could sing in.
你爸爸也给我了
And that's what your daddy gave me.
我不知道该怎样跟上他的步伐
I didn't know to keep up his strength,
我得牺牲自己
I had to give up little pieces of mine.
我把他的生活当做是我的生活
I took on his life as mine and mixed up the pieces,
以致难以分辨到底那是我的, 还是他的生活 [成全他]
so you couldn't hardly tell which was which.
那是我的选择, 放弃我的人生
It was my choice. My life.
而我根本不用那样屈就自己啊
And I didn't have to live it like that,
但那是我作为女人得做的
but that's what life offered me in the way of being a woman,
而我也接受了
and I took it.
我全然接受了
I grabbed it with both hands.
当Raynell来到我们家里时
And by the time Raynell came into the house...
我不想从别人的不幸上得到快乐
I didn't want to make my blessings off of nobody's misfortune,
但我依然把Raynell当作
but I took on to Raynell like she was
我想要但却从没有过的孩子
all them babies I wanted and never had.
就像我可以取回我原本的人生, 即使那么一点也好
Like I'd been blessed to relive a part of my life.
如果上帝认为有需要的话
And if the lord see fit to keep up my strength,
我会像你爸爸对你那样对待她
I'm gonna do her exactly how your daddy did you.
我会把我最好的都给她
I'm gonna give her the best of what's in me.
妈妈!
Mama!
Tolliver牧师打来了
Reverend Tolliver on the phone.
你好
Hi.
你在军队还是陆战队?
You in the army or the marines?
陆战队
Marines.
爸爸说你在军队, 你认识Blue吗?
Papa said it was army. You know Blue?
Blue? 谁是Blue?
Blue? Who's blue?
爸爸以前养的狗, 说起他时总会唱起歌来
Papa's dog, what he sing about all the time.
Here, Ring. Yeah, Ring Here
I had an old dog whose name was Blue
You know that Blue was mighty true
You know Blue was a good old dog
Blue treed a 'possum in a hollow log
From that you know Blue's a good old dog
Here, Ring. Yeah, Ring Here
Blue treed a 'possum out on a limb
Blue looked at me and I looked at him
Grabbed that 'possum and put him in a sack
Do fer me, Blue, 'til I get back
Old Blue's feet was big and round
Never 'lowed a 'possum to tech the ground
Old Blue died and I dug his grave
I dug his grave with a silver spade
I let him down with a golden chain
And every link I called his name
Go on Blue you good dog you
一起唱
Come on.
Go on Blue you good dog you
Blue laid down and died like a man
Blue laid down and died...
Now he's treein' 'possums in the promised land
I'm goin' to tell you this jes' to let you know
Old Blue's gone where the good dogs go
Cory, 我们得准备起行了
Cory, we're getting ready to leave now!
听妈妈的话, 上去换好鞋子
Go upstairs and put your shoes on like mama told you,
然后去爸爸的葬礼
so we can get ready to go to papa's funeral.
好的, 一会见
Okay. I'll be back.
Rose!
嘿, Rose!
Hey, Rose!
- Gabe?   - 我来了, Rose!
- Gabe?   - I'm here! I'm here, Rose!
嘿, Rose, 我来了!
Hey, Rose, I'm here!
- Lyons, 看看是谁!   - 看, Rose?
- Lyons, lookit here!    - See, Rose?
我就知道, 我说过他们会让他来
I told you. I told you they'd let him come.
- 你好吗, Gabe叔叔?   - 你好吗, Gabe叔叔?
- How you doing, Uncle Gabe? - How you doing, Uncle Gabe?
嘿, Rose, 是时候了!
Hey! Hey, Rose, it's time!
是时候叫圣彼得打开天堂之门了
It's time to tell Saint Peter to open the gates.
你准备好了吗, Troy?
You ready, Troy? Troy, you ready?
我要叫圣彼得打开门了
I'm gonna tell Saint Peter to open the gates.
你快准备好
You get ready now.
Troy!
Troy.
这就对了
That's the way that go.